<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of such greiuous accidents as commonly follow the biting of mad dogges, together with the cure thereof, by Thomas Spackman Doctor of Physick</title>
            <author>Spackman, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 860:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of such greiuous accidents as commonly follow the biting of mad dogges, together with the cure thereof, by Thomas Spackman Doctor of Physick</title>
                  <author>Spackman, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72, 75-83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of a madde dogges biting and the cure.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rabies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18279:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18279:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF SVCH GREIVOVS accidents as commonly follow the biting of mad Dogges, together with the cure thereof,</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS SPACKMAN Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>mad dog</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iohn Bill</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18279:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18279:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT VVROTH <hi>Knight, health and</hi> happines.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing collected out of many learned <hi>Authors,</hi> ſundry ſpeciall notes and obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhewing what ſtrang and cruell accidents, doe vſually or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often, follow the bitings of madde dogges, and knowing that among vs ſometimes (though not ſo frequently as in hotter countries) this miſcheife hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to the great danger both of man &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18279:3"/>beaſt: I am bould to preſent them (han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled and diſpoſed as they be) to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall view, (I hope) for p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>licke good, and to your particular ſelfe in reſpect of your worth and neighbourhoode. Our language (for ought J know) hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet ſaid ſo much of this ſubiect. Therefore if any by this ſhall take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſearch further, or ſpeake more for a greater generall good, J ſhalbe glad to be a whetſtone to ſuch an edge. Jn the meane time, ſeing this familiar animal, the Dog, is the ſeruant of poore men, the delight of great men, and a companion of moſt men: to preuent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences that may fall, <hi>Pecori, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> magiſtro,</hi> both to this kinde cattell, and their louing keepers, as alſo to prepare (if need require) a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient remedie for ſo diſaſtrous a miſhap,
<pb facs="tcp:18279:3"/>J haue thought good, thus (as J can) to forewarne their negligence that thinke ſlightly of ſuch a wound, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their ignorance, that may be (when time is) to ſeeke for needfull help, and make bould to direct theſe my ſimple labours, firſt and cheefely to your curteous acceptation, not as thankes for any benefites receiued, (for J am a ſtranger to you) nor as meanes to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate for future fauours (though it now be my hap to be your poore welwiſhing neighbour) but both for the popular and well deſerued ſpeeches the whole country doth aforde you, and alſo for that J know your place and pleaſure is, to keepe many Hounds for Hare and Deare, and Spaniels for land and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Accept therefore worthie <hi>SIR,</hi> this worthles) though perhaps not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:18279:4"/>fruitles) labour, as it is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a ſlender token of the good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reſpect J beare to the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your <hi>reputation.</hi> And ſo with my beſt wiſhes of health and happines to you, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips in all good will, THO. SPACKMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18279:4"/>
            <head>OF THE MADDE DOGGE: <hi>together with the Cure of thoſe moſt</hi> dangerous wounds and fearefull <hi>accidents, hapning to man and</hi> beaſt through their <hi>bitings.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F poyſons incident to the outward parts of man or beaſt, there is none that in the end induceth or procureth more cruell accidents, and fearefull affections, then the byting of a mad dogge, though in ſome more or leſſe then in other, partly by reaſon of the complexion and conſtitution of the body that is bitten, and partly by the manner of the byting.</p>
            <p>As for example, if a cholericke body of large vaines repleate with hot humors, be bitten through the skinne by a mad dogge, that with his byting ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth forth ſtore of that virulent ſome or matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in his mouth, being ſharpe and hot, he will become mad commonly in the ſpace of one month after he is bitten, and ſome time ſooner, as within a weeke, eſpecially if it be in the heate of ſommer, and copled with other bad cauſes, as an apt diſpoſition of the body, thereto &amp;c. If timely preuention be not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18279:5"/>vſed. And the worſer conſtitution of body a man is of, the more dangerous is the byting: but if the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten body bee of a cold complexion, ſuch as are the phlegmatike or melancholike, or the biting but ſlight, or the venemous matter proceeding from the dogge, but ſmall in quantity, or not very maligne &amp; pearcing, then is it longer before the bitten body be tainted with madnes. And by this reaſon it hath come to paſſe, that ſome after the biting haue felt no hurt (more then a little ache and ſmarting of the wound) till a quarter of a yeere after. Some not in a yeere or two,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or three, or 7. yea (as <hi>Galen</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, ſome not till 16. yeeres after, or as <hi>Guanerius,</hi> not till 18. yeeres after, which he verifieth by a ſtory of one that ſo many yeeres after he was bitten, fell mad and died ſo within three daies after. For ſuch is the condition of this poiſon, that when it hath lyen lurking in the body long before it be perceiued, it breaketh out, when it beginneth to ſtir, with much more violence, and maketh a quicker diſpatch, then otherwiſe. Which if we duly conſider, it is no wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for any man, be he neuer ſo lightly hurt, or feele as little preſent paine as may be thereby, to be ſecure and careles in ſeeking preſent remedy vpon ſuch a chaunce. For by often experience it hath been ſeene, that not only the biting is of force to cauſe madnes, but euen the fome or ſlauer of a mad dogs mouth, if it touch any bare part of the body, and be not ſpeedily wipt or waſht away with ſalt water, or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine of a boy, or ſuch like, eſpecially if any skin be broken where the ſlauer abideth, or the body bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be tender, thin skinned, weake or repleat with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18279:5"/>bad humours; ſuch being the ſubtill and pearcing nature thereof, that it ſpeedily paſſeth through the poores of the skin, and then by little and little ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it ſelfe way into the ſmall vaines, arteries and ſinowes, &amp; ſo in proceſſe of time aſſaileth the heart, and diſturbeth the braine.</p>
            <p>Now then if ſo great hurt may proceed from dogges, why doe we make them ſo familiar compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions with vs, and vſe them with ſo great delight, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we may endanger our ſelues thereby ſooner and ſorer then we imagine? Surely the reaſon is, becauſe the dogge is ſo neceſſarie a beaſt as men cannot well tell how to want. For the Maſtife dogge is a moſt truſtie ſeruant in a country houſe, a Butchers one hand, and by his admirable hardines maketh many great men in loue with him, for the delight and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime he giueth them in combating with the terrible Bull and merciles Beare. Yea ſome of them be ſo full of audacitie, that they will aduenture on the Lyon the King of beaſtes. But therein I commend them not, becauſe it ſauoureth of a rebellions nature, then which nothing can be more odious in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <p>Beſide the Maſtife, we haue other dogs of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as the land and water Spannels, the one neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for ſuch as delight in hawking after the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge and feſant, the other for water ſowles: the gentlemanly Greyhound for courſing Bucke, Stag, Otter or Hare: the Talbot or Buckhound, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded of noble perſonages: the hounds of ordinary Gentlemen and Yeomen, for Hare, Fox, &amp; Badger. Beſides theſe, we haue dogs, as of leſſer ſpirit and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18279:6"/>courage, ſo leſſe ſeemely and neceſſarie, and yet wel liked of many, as the Shepheards curre, which hee would not change for the beſt hound the King hath, &amp; ſondry other countrie curs, which ſome keep only to be as watchmen in the night, to lugge a Hog and eate vp their ſuperfluous cruſts and parings. And laſtly, wee muſt not forget the fine Lady dog that fares of the beſt, lodgeth warme and ſoft, and is trickt vp with ſiluer bels, carefully kept from flees, waſht and combed with great curioſitie, and hath more of this worldly pleaſure then many a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and honeſt houſe-keeper.</p>
            <p>Heare we ſee ſuch vſe and acceptation of all theſe ſorts of dogs, as we cannot well ſpare any of them, who beſide, make themſelues the better to be liked, becauſe they carry ſo true and hearty loue toward ſuch as they ſerue, as no brute creatures may be compared with them. As I remember a ſtory of which <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> is reported to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, wherein is ſhowne an admirable loue of a dog to his Maſter. The ſtorie is thus: A certaine Prieſt that had a louing dogge, on a time trauailing by the way, was met by a theefe that bereft him both of his mony and life, caſting his dead body into anod cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of the way, and ſo departed. The dog would not leaue his Maſters body though dead, but lay by it howling and crying day and night, till by this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead body was ſound, which being laid open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be viewed, the dog ſtill gaue his attendance thereon. At length, among other beholders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, came the theefe that robbed and murthered him, making ſhowe of as great ſorrow as any other: but
<pb facs="tcp:18279:6"/>the dog hauing ſpied him, ran at him, and would neuer leaue aſſayling and barking at him, till the reſt of the beholders by noting the dogs demeanour and his former attendance on the dead body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſuſpitious of him that he ſo fiercely aſſailed: whereupon cauſing him to bee throughly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he confeſſed the fact, and was dealt withall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deſert.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scaliger</hi> alſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exercit.</hi> 202.</note> maketh mention of a certaine huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that by extremitie of cold, was found dead on the top of a ſnowie mountaine, by whoſe dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die lay a great dog, keeping it in ſuch ſort, as he would ſuffer no man, neither the dead mans frends nor any other, not ſo much as ſuch as the dog be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did know and was acquainted withall, to touch or come neere it.</p>
            <p>But hauing no need to ſeeke ſo farre for ancient and forreine ſtories, <hi>Thomas Lupton</hi> in his notes of memorable things, maketh report of no leſſe loue in a dog than this, that ſerued an Inkeeper of <hi>Ware,</hi> a through-faire village in the way to and from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> This dog loued his Maſter ſo exceedingly, that after he was dead, he ſought him vp and down certaine daies, with ſo great ſorrow and mourning, as nothing could comfort him, neither would he eat or drinke at all. At length, not finding him whom he ſo carefully ſought for, he laid himſelfe downe in the hot coales in the chimney, from whence being pluckt diuers times, he notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding would doe ſo ſtill, till he had burnt himſelfe to death. Though many wiues loue their huſbands dearely, yet I thinke very few of them would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb facs="tcp:18279:7"/>to make demonſtration of their loue by ſuch a concluſion.</p>
            <p>As by theſe examples, the exceeding loue of dogs toward ſuch as they ſerue, is noted for one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſe of the regard that is made of them, ſo are they beſides this, much eſteemed for their ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wittie capacitie in learning many pretty and ſtrange things.</p>
            <p>But as for theſe and ſuch like cauſes we loue and like them, ſo if we would conſider well the great hurts they often do, and may procure both to man and beaſt by their madneſſe, which no creature is thought ſo ſubiect vnto as they, we ſhould rather prouidently haue an eye to them and beware of them, then ſo familiarly entertaine them as we doe: eſpecially, if we did bethinke our ſelues that this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie betwixt vs and them, maketh vs the leſſe circumſpect in preuenting the hurt which in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we may catch by them. For ſome Writers affirme, that there is no meanes to helpe or cure ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man or beaſt, that by the byting of a mad dog are become mad.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> And <hi>Paulus Aegineta</hi> ſaith, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner knew aboue one or two cured of this kinde of madneſſe, and thoſe not immediately bitten of a dog, but bitten of ſuch perſons as were fallen mad by the byting of a mad dog. Now if any deſire to know into what kind of paſſions ſuch doe fall as are bitten of theſe creatures, and not holpen before they be growen mad, let them marke theſe ſtories following.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Baldus</hi> of <hi>Trident,</hi> Doctor of both lawes, and a very famous man in his profeſſion, had a litle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18279:7"/>fine Lady dog, that he did take much delight in, and would often play with him. This dogge on a time (as <hi>Mathiolus</hi> reporteth) ſnapt his Maſter by the lip, yet ſo lightly as he made none account of the hurt, neither had the leaſt ſuſpition that might bee of the dogs madneſſe. But hereupon, about ſome foure moneths after, this famous Lawyer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo lawleſſe, ſo vnruly, ſo outragious, and ſo far beſide humane ſenſe and behauiour, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the meanes which were vſed for helpe, he died in that madneſſe very miſerably.</p>
            <p>This may bee an admonition to all ſuch fine La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Gentlewomen as take pleaſure in playing with their beloued chamber-dogs, to haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardfull eye to their chaps.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Andraeas Baccius Elpidianus</hi> a learned Phyſition, writeth thus of a Patient of his that was bitten by a mad dog, although with ſo ſmal hurt and offence, as he regarded it not, hauing the wound healed vp within the ſpace of three daies. But about a month being paſt, finding himſelfe more ſad and ſorrowful than he was wont to be, together with a loathing of himſelfe, and wondring how it ſhould ſo come to paſſe, he ſent for me (ſaith <hi>Baccius</hi>) inquiring the reaſon and cauſe thereof, and I finding him weake ſpirited and lompiſh, aduiſed him to be carefull of his diet, to feed vpon comfortable meates and eaſie of digeſtion, and to drinke wine for the better ſtrengthning of his ſpirits, more plentifully than he had vſed to doe. To which he anſwered, that hee could neither cat nor drinke, whereupon I offering him drinke, and noting his impotencie in receiuing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18279:8"/>it, opened his mouth, but found no cauſe there, of his weakneſſe or refuſall. Then after long bethin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my ſelfe what might be the cauſe thereof, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him whether at any time he had been bitten by any dog. To which he anſwered, yes, but yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great hurt, as he thought. Wherupon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome words of comfort, I acquainted his wife and other of his friends priuately, what danger hee was in, wiſhing them to boat him ouer the riuer <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> by which he dwelt, and ſodenly to throw him in, and ſowſe him well in the water, which they did, himſelfe being very willing thereto. But this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe profiting nothing, I made tryall of other meanes vſed in ſuch caſes, but all in vaine. For the ſame day toward night, hee began to rage, and though tormented with intollerable thirſt, and a troubleſome feuer, yet could he not be forced to drinke any kinde of drinke or water, (which is a common accident in this diſeaſe.) Then was hee ſtrongly bound to a poſt, yet ſo great was his furie and madneſſe, that he had almoſt broken the cords, with a deſire to runne vpon the by-ſtanders, crying away, away; and ſometime howling like a dog, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping wide, tormented with thirſt, and as it were holding his mouth open for drinke, but when it was caſt into his mouth with a ſpout, hee would tremble and quake for feare, continuing in this manner moſt cruelly vexed with inſufferable thirſt and helliſh heat and burning, vntill the ſecond day from the beginning of his madneſſe, was neere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and then hee yeelded vp the ghoſt in wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full torture, and no leſſe terrour and aſtoniſhment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18279:8"/>to the beholders, being the 36 day after his biting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iulianus Palmarius</hi> alſo writeth, that hee knew a man of the country bitten with a mad dogge, who in like maner became mad, &amp; ſo furious, that he was bound with cordes for reſtraint of his fury, and the hurt he was like to doe vnto others. Yet ſometime this man found intermiſſion of his fits, in ſuch ſort as he then would ſpeake and talke ſenſiblie, and would yeld to reaſon. And on a time, in ſuch a kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion and ſenſibleneſſe, making account hee ſhould die very ſhortlie, he deſired ſuch as were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, that he might take his leaue of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: which being permitted, he embraced and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them very louingly, and very ſhortly after, hee yeelded vp the ghoſt. But about 7 dayes after, theſe his children became as mad as their father, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vexed with the like tortures, died within few daies very pitifully tormented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieronymus Cardanus</hi> in like maner ſheweth that one <hi>Alexander Braſca,</hi> a nobleman of <hi>Venice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Conten. Medico. Tract.</hi> 5.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a dogge fallen mad that he exceedingly loued, which for his madneſſe was taken to be hanged, this man in a fooliſh kindneſſe, would needs kiſſe his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued dogge before his execution. But ſuch was the ſequel of this kiſſing, as himſelfe became mad al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in very ſhort ſpace after, and died very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matthaeus de Gradibus</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſ.</hi> 82.</note> that one <hi>Iohn Coque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> by the only putting of his hand into a mad dogs mouth, became mad himſelfe thereby. And <hi>P. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draeas Matthiolus</hi> teſtifieth, that he ſaw two men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with this kinde of madneſſe, by the only ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18279:9"/>of a mad dogges ſlauer vpon them, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bitten at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſta Codronchus</hi> a late writer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iab.</hi> 1. <hi>de Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophob. cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſaith he knew a certaine rich man of Saint Peters caſtle in the dition of <hi>Bononia,</hi> who ſeeing a little dogge of his that hee dearely loued, enraged ſo with madneſſe, as he ran vp and downe gaping and foaming at the mouth, he ſuppoſing that ſome bone had ſtucke in his mouth or throat, would needs trie with his hand, the pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out therof, but was for his kindneſſe ſo bitten by this his darling, that thereupon he became cruelly tortured with the feare of water and conuulſions, and the ſeuenth day after in great miſerie and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tooke his leaue of this world. He was twice or thrice caſt into the water and enforced to drinke it, but without any reliefe at all. Heereby we may ſee, not onely the cruelty of this kinde of poyſon, but alſo learne to take heed of it in time. But though the foame or ſlauer of a mad dogge be by all mens conſent, of a moſt virulent nature, yet <hi>Petrus Salius Diuerſus</hi> a very learned and intelligent Phyſitian, cannot be perſwaded, that by only touching of the skinne of ones bodie, it can be of force to procure madneſſe, except the skin bee broken in that part which the foame toucheth. Yet ſurely I for my part doe verily beleeue, that if it be ſuffred to lie long vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſound skin, it will worke ſuch an effect in the end, in ſome ſooner, in ſome later, according to the conſtitution and diſpoſition of the partie bitten, and the poyſonous degree of ſuch filthy ſlauer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> an ancient writer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt.</hi> 6. <hi>lib.</hi> 18. <hi>in vita Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij Tyanei.</hi>
               </note> hath a ſtorie of a young man, that being bitten with a mad dog, was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18279:9"/>within a little while after ſo altred from all humane manners and conditions, that he became altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dog-like in his behauiour. For he would barke, and ſit on the ground like a dogge, and when he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to go, it was ſtill vpon all foure, vſing his hands as his feet, as apes doe, continuing in this wretched eſtate the ſpace of thirty dayes together, <hi>Iulian Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marius</hi> before named, affirmeth that hee had ſeene horſes, oxen, ſheepe, and other cattel become mad vpon the eating of ſuch ſtraw or hay, as mad ſwine had tumbled in.</p>
            <p>Yet this is a miſchiefe that few people hitherto haue greatly made account of; which ſlight regard of a thing ſo full of perill, hath beene one ſpeciall cauſe, that hath moued mee to publiſh the danger thereof, in ſuch maner as by the beholding of other mens harmes, the readers heereof may heerafter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more circumſpect and warie, and when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſerueth ſeeke remedy with ſpeed.</p>
            <p>This kind of madneſſe is called in greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in latine <hi>Rabies,</hi> or <hi>Furor,</hi> of the Greeke verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1. <hi>Rabie percellor, inſanio.</hi> The greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth alſo ſignifie <hi>furorem,</hi> furie, but that is ſuch a maner of fury as belongeth to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bruit beaſts. And <hi>Rabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> taken rather for doggiſh-madnes, then <hi>furor,</hi> hath this propertie attributed to it, that although the ſicke therof be extreamly tormented with thirſt and heat, yet doe they ſo wonderfully abhorre and feare the ſight, yea (as ſome haue obſerued) the very noiſe or ſpeech of water and other drinke, as they will in no wiſe taſte thereof, but tremble and quake
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18279:10"/>when they looke on it, and therefore by all meanes auoid it. Some in ſtead of <hi>rabies,</hi> call it <hi>hydrophobia</hi> that is to ſay water-feare. But this ſeemeth rather a conſequent to <hi>rabies,</hi> and to come vpon the ſtage in the very laſt act of this tragedie.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe was not in a matter of ſuch a ſubiect, as may be ſhut vp in ſo ſmal a roome as this, to ſtand curiouſly vpon any bookiſh method for the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heere of; but rather as compendiouſlie without multiplicitie of words, as I could, to ſet abroach the knowledge thereof in our vulgar language, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a caueat or watch-word, to al ſuch as haue vſe and dealing with dogges: though notwithſtanding I thinke it not amiſſe, heere to ſhew ſome definition or deſcription of this infirmitie, for the plaine expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of it: although very few haue vouchſaued ſo much in the treatie hereof: &amp; therfore for auoiding of tediouſnes I will produce only one, which in my conceit doth more ſignificantly expreſſe the nature of this infirmitie, then any other that I haue read, which is thus out of <hi>Baptista Codronchus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rabies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droph. Cap.</hi> 1.</note> That is to ſay, Doggiſh madneſſe, is an affect beſide nature, ingendred or bred in a liuing creature, of ſome certaine peculiar poyſon, and communicated or imparted to man with a veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deteſtation of all liquid things, but eſpecially of water.</p>
            <p>Heereby we may ſee the originall of this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from ſuch kind of poyſon, as by the peculiar propertie thereof, induceth a greater loathing of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid things, then any other manner of poyſon is knowen to doe.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18279:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> ſaith he hath knowen ſome of theſe mad people, that would eat bread and fleſh, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſugar, in great quantitie, while they were tortured with their madfits, but if the ſugar were diſſolued in wine, broth, or water, they would in no wiſe taſte thereof. And many of them will howle and barke like dogs. Though this manner of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be accounted ſo peculiar and proper to dogges as no creatures are found ſo often afflicted therwith as dogges, and ſuch as haue beene bitten with dogs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating the poyſon thereof one to another by contagion: yet <hi>Palmarius</hi> ſaith, hee ſaw twentie woolues at one time enraged with this kind of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ranne forth of a wood together, byting and murthering great numbers of all ſorts of cattell. But what are woolues indeed, other then a kinde of wilde dogges?</p>
            <p>Howbeit <hi>Andraeas Baccius</hi> affirmeth that the kinde of Weaſils called Martynnes, and Apes alſo, haue primarilie (that is without the byting of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature) beene found mad. He maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo of a woman that being bitten by a cat, fell mad, and died within 14 dayes after.</p>
            <p>And againe he ſaith, that he knew a certaine Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner, who vpon the ſodaine was aſſailed with an old red cocke, and bitten by him on the left-hand that it bled withall. Which Gardiner, the very ſame day ſhewed his teeth and grinned like a dogge, and ſtreight after he offred to leape like a fighting cocke, at ſuch as were neere him, with fierce and ſtaring eyes, and the third day after his biting he died in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the terrour of the behoulders. But it is like,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18279:11"/>in mine opinion, that both this Cat and Cocke were firſt bitten by ſome mad dogge, and this laſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe he made a grinning and ſhowe of his teeth like a dogge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alſo ſaith that Camels, Horſes &amp; Mules haue beene found mad in like ſort,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>de Hiſt. animalium.</hi>
               </note> and my ſelfe knew a Mare of great worth, that was mad, but ſhe had beene bitten by the noſe by a mad dog. And ſwine I haue knowne mad vpon the like occaſion, and ſo I am perſwaded that the other creatures named by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> gat their bane alſo from madde dogges. Yet <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> ſhoweth ſome reaſon to proue that this kind of madnes may be cauſed in man or beaſt, by ſome internall principle inbred within them, with out the biting or contagion from any other. And to that end he produceth a ſtory of a woman his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in manner following.</p>
            <p>A certaine woman about 36. yeeres of age, ſicke of a feuer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de affect. Particula. Cap.</hi> 19.</note> ſent for me crauing my help. Being come, I perceiued that ſhe was vexed with a peſtilent fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, whoſe cure I take in hand, and the 11. day after, I left her reſtored to health. About ſo many daies after, ſhe fell ſicke againe of a bloudy flix and a feuer withall. Wherupon ſhe ſent for me the ſecond time, and hereof I holpt her in the ſpace of 7. daies, ſauing that a light or mild feuer ſtill remained, of whoſe cure I did deliberate. But before I could effect it, the woman fell into a great loathing and abhorring of all liquid things, and that ſo exceedingly, as ſhe would neither receiue any her ſelfe, nor could abide to ſee any other body drinke before her, it being in the middeſt of ſommer. Whereupon I ſuppoſed her
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18279:11"/>to be ſicke of a doggiſh madnes called <hi>rabies.</hi> Yet ſhe was well in her wits and vnderſtanding, complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of nothing ſo much, as the deteſtation of drinke or liquid meates, the ſight or imagination whereof, miniſtred ſo great horror vnto her as was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Otherwiſe ſhe was very quiet, and would talke very ſenſibly. Whereupon I asked whether ſhe had not at any time beene bitten of dogges? To which ſhe anſwered no, neither did euer keepe any dog in the houſe. Then I asked her Mother alſo whether ſhe had not been bitten when ſhe was a little Girle or Infant? who alſo anſwered the like. Vpon conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration whereof I began to doubt whether any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy might fall into this kind of affliction or hydropho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie by ſome inbred beginning or occasſion, without contagion from any other. The woman could not be cured hereof, but the eight day after died in this manner of paſſion. The reaſon of this hydrophobie or water-feare in this woman, I leaue to be diſcuſſed of the learned. But in mine opinion this was the leſſe like to proceed from the biting of a mad dogge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not accompanied with any other of ſuch accidents as are vſually wont to goe with it. And though this example be <hi>ex raro contingentibus,</hi> in a manner matchles, yet <hi>Soranus</hi> ſeemeth to parallel this of <hi>Salius</hi> by a hiſtorie that he reporteth of a child, whom he ſaw ſo fearefull of his nurces breaſt-milke, that it would not abide to taſt it, yet no note or knowledge of doggiſh contagion going before.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18279:12"/>
               <head>Cauſes of this infirmitie.</head>
               <p>IN ſearching out the cauſes of this doggiſh mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diuers learned writers both olde and new, haue been very induſtrious, producing reaſons agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the opinions they were of, which heere to ſet downe in order, would be more long and tedious, then pleaſing &amp; profitable, and therefore I will ſhow breefly ſuch as ſeeme moſt probable and truth-like. Of which ſome are immediate and inward: other ſome mediate and outward. The immediate and inward cauſe hereof, is a moſt pernicious and deadly poiſon ingendred and bred of ſuch corruption of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and notable malignitie, as peculiarly forteth and moſt agreeth to the nature of ſuch creatures, as are afflicted therewith.</p>
               <p>Corruption and prauity of humors, is the mediate inward cauſe of ſuch manner of poiſon, as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of heat and cold, a hot and dry region, or ſuch as is extreamely cold and dry, are the mediate out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſes. All which argue that the temperature and complexion of dogges, is not any efficient cauſe of this infirmitie, though like enough to yeeld ſome furtherance thereto. For if dogges (being very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie beaſtes) be reſtrained or kept much from drinke, choler doth ſo boile in them (as ſome thinke) that it ioyned with the peculiar propertie of their nature, helpeth forward the breeding of ſuch a malignitie as forceth them to madnes. Which may happen at any time of the yeere, but eſpecially in the heat of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that cheefly in the dogge daies, or in the extremitie of winter. For both theſe conſtitutions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18279:12"/>of the aire, though contrary, may worke the ſame effect. For as the extremitie of heat is of force to ſcortch the blood, ſo the extremitie of cold, doth thicken and congeale it in ſuch ſort, as for want of difflation it be commeth groſſe and blacke, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by infected with ſo euill a qualitie, as giueth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of madnes. And therefore in theſe regions where the Sommer ſeaſon is moſt hot, and the winter moſt cold, are commonly found moſt ſtore of ſuch dogs. But the very true cauſe indeed why a dogge is more quickely &amp; eaſily turned mad then any creature els, is his peculiar and naturall propertie and inclination to ſuch a maladie, more then of any other liuing creature.</p>
               <p>Among outward cauſes contagion or the byting one of an other is the chiefe. Their feeding alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carion, eſpecially ſuch as haue died of any murri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or rot, or been ſtriken dead with thunder, or poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by the biting or ſtinging of any venemous beaſtes: or their eating of corrupt, rotten, ſtinking or very ſalt or ſpiced meates: much ſorrow for want of their loſt maſters: for hereupon many times, they hunt vp and downe ſo long, without eating or drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that by their reſtles trauaile, want of meat and drinke, ioyned with mourning &amp; greife, their blood is ſo chafed and diſtempered, as it miniſtreth great occaſion of breeding this kinde of fearefull paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For as dogges doe exceedingly loue thoſe whom they ſerue, ſo will they as much greeue for the loſſe of them.</p>
               <p>A dogs loue ſaith <hi>Aſcanius Mancinellus</hi> hath this peculiar propertie aboue the loue of other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18279:13"/>that the more his Maſter beateth him, the more entirely he will loue him, and thereupon in a merry conceit, hee ſeemeth to prooue a womans loue and a dogs to bee contrarie one to the other, in that (as he ſaith) If a woman be beaten but once by her husband, ſhee will doe her vttermoſt to repay it againe a hundreth fold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aetius</hi> out of <hi>Rufus</hi> and <hi>Poſidonius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tetru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> ſaith, that dogs being hot and dry by nature, doe get an other kind of heat and dryneſſe in the Sommer time, by the ambient aire, and by the immoderate intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature thereof doe become mad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, that no creature is troubled with this kind of madneſſe, but onely dogs. Which ſpeech of his, hath tryed the wits of many men in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out the truth therof. Of whom, ſom thinke it vnderſtood by <hi>Galen,</hi> for the moſt part, or none ſo madde as dogs, or none vexed with ſuch a kinde of madneſſe primarily, that is, from their owne pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar nature, as dogs be, but that ſuch as are infected with this kinde of madneſſe, haue it commonly from dogges by contagion.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Galens</hi> words be theſe: <hi>Cum enim reliquorum animalium nullum rabie capian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſolus canis co affectu corripitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas A Viega</hi> commenting vpon theſe words ſaith: <hi>Lege (nullo alio capto) ſolus: ſignificat manenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus alijs multis ſanis, canem corripi ob promptitudinem temperamenti: non quaſi alia non rabiunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Salius,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Credatur hoc ab eo fuiſſe factum ob non habitam ab eo rei experientiam &amp;c.</hi> That is, Let it be ſuppoſed that <hi>Galen</hi> ſpake thus, not vpon any experience he had of this matter, which if he had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18279:13"/>ſeene, or heard any faithfull teſtimonie thereof, he would ſurely haue reuoked this opinion, and not haue auouched, that onely dogs and none other creatures are taynted with this manner of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſcanius Mancinellus</hi> endeuouring to explane <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> meaning, ſaith: <hi>Quando Galenus dicit canem ſolum &amp;c.</hi> That is, When <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith that a dog onely is troubled with this kind of madneſſe called <hi>rabies,</hi> it is to be vnderſtood, firſt and principally, by reaſon he is more apt thereto than any other liuing thing, but other creatures by a ſecondarie meanes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally: for that this <hi>rabies,</hi> which inferreth the terrible paſſion of water-feare, ſeemeth to bee the proper paſſion of dogs, as a thing more often and rather afflicting them, then other liuing creatures. Which ſeemeth the more probable, for that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, not one among a thouſand is found to be affected with this manner of madneſſe; and ſuch things as ſo ſeldom happen, are eſteemed as though they neuer hapned. Beſide this, the truth hereof ſeemeth more apparant, becauſe I neuer found in any author or expoſitor, that the ſignes and notes accompanying this diſeaſe, haue been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and ſpoken of in other mad beaſts, or that ſuch as haue been bitten by them, haue fallen into the paſſion of water-feare, as it falleth out in thoſe that are bitten by a mad dog. Therefore wee may very well conclude, that this kind of affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth properly and principally to dogs, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily to other creatures, and thereby it may ſeeme no abſurditie to ſay, that their madnes is not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18279:14"/>
                  <hi>vera rabies,</hi> becauſe it wants the right notes of <hi>rabies,</hi> but rather a kind of furie cauſed by aduſtion of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, according to part, and not according to the whole. And this I thinke may ſuffice for the expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Galens</hi> meaning, though more I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Signes of a madde Dogge.</head>
               <p>WHen a dog is become mad,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iacobus Greni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Venenis, cap.</hi> 35. <hi>&amp; alij.</hi>
                  </note> he is commonly altered in the whole habit and temperature of his body, growing leane, dry and thirſtie, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing drinke, and fearing or flying from water and bright things. He is ſad and penſiue, hanging down his head, or bearing it more toward one ſide than another: his eyes be red and fierie, his countenance horrible and very vnpleaſant; and <hi>Paulus</hi> ſaith hee is altogether dumbe and ſeldom able to barke. Yet ſome ſay, he will now and then barke at his owne ſhadow, but with a very hoarſe voice. His eares hang down, he dreueleth and fometh at the mouth and noſe, his tongue hangeth out, being of a red or blackiſh colour, hee bloweth ſhort, refuſeth both meat and drinke, his tayle hangeth looſely, or is clapt betwixt his legs: hee goeth drowſily, and when he runneth, he reeleth to and fro, yet runneth he then faſter then he was wont; hee knoweth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Maſter, nor any of the houſhold, but will bite them as ſoone as any other. What creature ſoeuer he meeteth, either wilde or tame, he will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to bite it. In his running or going, he will ſtop ſomtime vpon the ſudden. All other dogs are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18279:14"/>of him, and runne from him if they may: but if they meet him on the ſudden, they will crouch downe to him and flatter him for feare.</p>
               <p>Theſe are noted to bee the ſignes of an abſolute mad dog, but many mad dogs want ſome of theſe ſignes.</p>
               <p>Therefore when one is bitten with any dogge whatſoeuer, becauſe <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. de ther. ad Piſon. cap.</hi> 16.</note> that the byting of a mad dog, is like, and nothing different in ſhow or feeling, from the byting of one that is not madde. <hi>Oribaſius,</hi> and other ancient Writers, ſet downe this for a tryall, namely, to take the kernell of a Wainut well bruiſed, and lay it vpon the bitten place, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Greeke writers, a day and a night, but <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Haly abbas,</hi> thinke a night ſufficient, <hi>Auicen,</hi> onely an hower, of which opinion is <hi>Gentilis,</hi> if the kernell be applied preſently after the byting, but otherwiſe not. Some againe ſay, if the wound be great and bleed much, that an hower is ſufficient, becauſe that in great wounds a nut will much ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner drink vp the poyſon than in ſmal. Therfore the ſmaller wounds require a longer time. When it is taken of, caſt it to Hens, who if they eat it and dye the next day after, it is a manifeſt ſigne that the dog was mad; or as ſome ſay, if they refuſe to eat it. Or take a peece of bread, wet in the bleeding wound of one bitten, then offer the ſame to ſome other hungry dog to eat; if he refuſe to taſte of it, that is taken for a very had ſigne. Yet ſome thinke that theſe are not ſufficient tryalls to repoſe truſt vpon, and therefore it were better to note diligently whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the byting dog be afraid of water or not, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18279:15"/>that is accounted a certaine ſigne of madneſſe, if he feare and refuſe the ſight of it. This kind of feare is named of the Greekes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is for the moſt part, an inſeparable ſigne of a mad dog, or of any other thing that is mad by the byting of a dog. Neither can they abide the ſight of any thing that is bright, as to behold a looking glaſſe, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Among dogs, ſuch are noted to be moſt apt to become mad, as are ſwifteſt of foot, fulleſt of agility in body, leaneſt of conſtitution, and in colour red or blacke.</p>
               <p>A man bitten of a mad dog, firſt becommeth ſad and full of imaginations, after the poyſon begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth once to worke, muttering and talking to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and being asked a queſtion, anſwereth litle to the purpoſe. He is afraid, where is no cauſe of feare, his ſleepe weareth away, he feeleth gry pings in his ſtomacke, and ſhunneth the companie of men; his countenance becommeth wild and gaſtly, hee is exceeding thirſtie, his voice groweth hoarſe, his eyes red and fierie, flying the light, and ſomtime weepeth without any manifeſt cauſe; his face ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee is very prone to anger more than hee was wont to be, his minde is far out of order. For the venome hauing made it ſelfe a way through the ſmall veines and arteries into the great, in proceſſe of time getteth vp to the braine, where it peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and corrupteth the imagination, reaſon, and memorie. Yea ſometime it ſo infecteth the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowes, as hee is vexed with grieuous crampes, and cruell convulſions, and in the end forceth him ſo far out of his wits, as hee will offer violence both to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18279:15"/>himſelfe and all that he is in companie withall, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with his teeth like a dog, and will howle and barke after a doggiſh manner, fearing the ſight of water, or any bright thing, and (as ſome Writers affirme) imagining that therein hee ſeeth a dogge, which of all creatures hee feareth and abhorreth moſt.</p>
               <p>Beſide theſe remembred notes, <hi>Salius</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth one, which he auoucheth to be infallible, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neuer obſerued before by any but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: which is a feeling of ſome kind of paine in the bitten place, though the wound haue been healed long before. For when the bitten body beginneth to grow into madneſſe, he ſenſibly feeleth a paine, though not very great, in the place that he was bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in, which creeping from place to place, about three or fower dayes after it beginneth, or a little more, aſcendeth to the brayne, where it cauſeth a kind of giddyneſſe and a certaine manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion withall, whereby the ſicke bodie beginneth to ſtagger and reele this way and that way, and ſhortly after, falleth ſtarke mad.</p>
               <p>This ſenſible feeling of paine in the bitten place when the mad humour beginneth to ſtirre, which <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> calleth an infallible note of this mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, neuer before obſerued by any but himſelfe, as he ſayth, ſeemeth to be verified by a ſtory of a mad body, related by an excellent Phyſition called <hi>D. Abel Roſcius</hi> of <hi>Lauſanna,</hi> in an epiſtle of his to <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel. Fabritius</hi> that notable Chirurgion of our time. The ſtory as he hath reported it, is, as followeth.</p>
               <p>A certaine very honeſt Matron, the daughter of
<pb facs="tcp:18279:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18279:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18279:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18279:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18279:18"/>a famous Doctor, and married not paſt two yeeres before to a Nobleman, one wel knowen to me, and very neere allied, as ſhe paſſed one day through the citie, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1581. was ſuddenly ſet vpon by a madde dogge and bitten in the left arme. The neighbours and other that were in her company, being much grieued at this miſhap, kild the dogge preſently, and without delay were learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians ſent for, who preſcribed exquiſite remedies, cauſing them to be applyed to the part affected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, not omitting the adminiſtration of wholſome antidotes and apt preſeruatiues inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The bitten arme was ſtreightly bound about the wound, and locall medicines of drawing facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the bringing forth of the venome, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. After which a Chirurgion ſeared the place with a hot iron, ſo that within a few dayes ſpace the woman (as it pleaſed God was quite healed) or ſeemed ſo to be, no hurt appearing in her arme, nor ſcarce any ſcarre perceiued, neither was there any ſuſpition of the leaſt iot of poyſon remaining. But marke I pray you what followed. In the ſeuenth yeere after it was healed, ſhee was afflicted with much more cruell and grieuous accidents: In the arme that was bitten ſhee felt a moſt intollerable paine, like as it had beene torne and gnawed with the teeth of dogs: Very ſhortly after, ſhe became furious, diſtract in minde, full of griefe and ſorrow, voyd of ſleepe, vexed with vnquenchable thirſt, and after this with a feuer and exceeding decay of ſtrength, abhorring meat extreamly, but not drink, neither did ſhe refuſe ſuch liquid things as might
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18279:18"/>aſſwage her thirſt. We thought her hard at deaths dore becauſe wee ſaw no hope of life or health in her. Yet ſo notable remedies were with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence adminiſtred to her by Phyſitians, and ſo well ſhe was attended by her domeſticals, as beyond all hope, ſhee recouered health againe in few dayes. Seuen yeeres after this inuaſion, and in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere after the dogges byting, and in the third yeere after the death of her husband, ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan againe to be moſt miſerably tortured, her fit ſtill beginning in her left arme. She felt extreame paines, was vexed with vomiting and incredible belching, enduring all the ſymptomes that are wont to proceed from burnt choler, want of ſleepe and exceeding thirſtineſſe. In the bitten place ſhee felt moſt cruell prickings ſhootings and exquiſite paines, yet by good meanes ſhe was againe holpen, I being ſtill preſent with her, and ſeemed perfectly cured. Howbeit, I deemed that her griefes were rather dulled and as it were brought a ſleepe, then quite extinguiſhed, although ſhe continued in this good ſtate ſix yeares together, as afterward it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. For in the twentieth yeere after her by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, her former griefes returned againe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet then alſo aſſwaged, they vexed her the next yeare following, and the very next yeere after this ſhe had to grieuous fits thereof, and the next after that, three, and this laſt yeere two. Her fits in the three former yeeres were oftner, but ſhorter. In almoſt euery one of the mutations of theſe times, her paines ſtill began in her bitten arme, I feare it will bee her death ſhortly. Of all this I am a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18279:19"/>and haue been ſtill preſent, &amp;c. Thus far <hi>D. Abel Roſcius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſtory is produced as a thing of rare contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. The chiefe cauſe of the ſo often redinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of theſe mad ſits in this Gentlewoman, (in mine opinion) was, for that the wound at the firſt curing thereof, was healed vp to ſoone. For it ſhould haue been kept open and from healing, the ſpace of fortie dayes at the leaſt: and again, becauſe the hot iron was applied before ſufficient abſtertion and correction of the venemous matter conteined therein, by conuenient lotions and the application of ventozes or horſeleeches, to the place affected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aetius,</hi> an ancient writer, reporteth a ſtory of a Phyloſopher, that being bitten with a mad dogge, and at length perceiuing his growing into that infirmitie, went to waſh himſelfe in a bath, wherein hee thought hee ſaw a dogge. Whereupon mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a pretty while, at length he tooke courage and lept into the bath, ſaying, what haue dogs to doe with bathes, and ſtriuing againſt the growing infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, dranke his belly full of the bath water, and ſo holpt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Dotage, or idle talking, hath been noted to bee one ſpeciall accident that vſually followeth ſuch as are growing into the extremitie of this cuill, thogh alwaies it falleth not out ſo. For <hi>Peter Salius</hi> before named, who had good experience of this bad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie, ſaith, he knew ſome in great extremitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſhow or token of dotage, and ſo ſenſible, that being perſuaded to drinke at ſuch time as they haue trembled at the ſight thereof, haue requeſted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18279:19"/>the offerers of it, that they would cloſe their eyes or blindfold them, that they might not ſee the drinke or water offered them, and then bad them caſt into their mouthes what they thought good, or any thing elſe mixt with their drinke that might be for their helpe. And when they grinned or gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with their teeth, and after a doggiſh faſhion, were forced by the ſtrength of the poyſon working in them, to offer to byte ſuch as were neere them, they would pray the by-ſtanders, to hold or binde them faſt, that they might not hurt any body by their byting, wiſhing them not to put their hands, or any part of their bodies to their mouthes, leſt they ſhould ſnap at them; for ſo the poyſonous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection enforced them to doe. Theſe, ſaith hee, I haue knowen to lament their owne miſerie, being greatly grieued, that they ſought not for helpe in due time, committing themſelues in all things to Gods mercy, crauing of him forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If a man that is fallen madde by the byting of a mad dog, doe byte an other man, woman, or child, they likewiſe will be mad in time, except by good meanes it be ſpeedily preuented. Yet this madnes cauſed by a mad mans byting, is much more eaſily preuented and cured, then the madneſſe of ſuch as haue it immediately from a dog. Howbeit, the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome mad men or women, that is, ſuch as be blacke or red hayred and freckled, is worſe than the byting of other colours: and among other, ſuch as be faſting.</p>
               <p>It hath beene much debated among Writers,
<pb facs="tcp:18279:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18279:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18279:21"/>which ſhould bee the chiefe and moſt ſpeciall place affected in this maladie; ſome thinking that the ſynnowes were, becauſe of the grieuous convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that the ſicke haue been vexed with ſomtimes. Other, that the brayne, in which reſteth the ſeat of the reaſonable ſoule. Some, the mouth of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, obſeruing their maner of vomiting, yexing, and inſatiable thirſt. Some, the heart onely. But others (whoſe opinion liketh me beſt) doe beleeue that not onely place or part of the body is affected therwith, but many, as the heart, ſtomacke, midrife, head, &amp;c. For if the venome doe firſt peirce the veines or arteries, it paſſeth directly to the liuer and heart. If it firſt take poſſeſſion of the ſynnowes, it mounteth thereby to the braine &amp; the membranes or skins encloſing it, whereupon follow ſuch terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble convulſions as they are many times afflicted withall, and by conſent from thence the mouth of the ſtomacke and conſequently the heart. For they are not troubled with any feuer till the heart bee touched, which indeed is the part that all manner of poyſon either mediately, or immediately doth inuade.</p>
               <p>Now if I be asked why mad dogs doe ſo greatly feare water,
<note place="margin">The cauſe of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophobia or water-feare.</note> For anſwer I will produce the opinions of ſundry learned Writers concerning this point.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieronymus Capinaccius</hi> out of <hi>Galen de theriaca ad Piſonem,</hi> bringeth this for one reaſon: Namely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a madde dog is ſo exceeding dry, as hee hath great need and deſire of moyſture, but being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract in his minde and perſeuerance, deſpiſeth it, and flieth from that which might doe him good.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18279:21"/>
               <p>This, and diuers other opinions of ancient and ſome moderne Writers, are learnedly diſproued by <hi>Baptista Codronchus,</hi> who afterward yeeldeth his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation to others more like to be true.</p>
               <p>But why do men which are reaſonable creatures, feare alſo and tremble at the ſight of water or other moyſture or liquors, when they be mad by the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mad dog?</p>
               <p>This ſaith <hi>Capinaccius,</hi> proceedeth from the great abundance of melancholy, that ſendeth vp a darke blacke vapour to the braine, whereby the animall ſpirit is made ſo thicke and cloudie, that the action thereof is hurt and perturbed.</p>
               <p>But why doe they feare water more than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obiect?</p>
               <p>Becauſe of the want of moyſture, which is in ſuch a manner, as the moyſt forme of water hath gotten a fearefull impreſſion hereof in the brayne.</p>
               <p>But if water be brought them, why is their feare ſometime increaſed, and ſometime they bee ready to vomit at the ſight thereof?</p>
               <p>They be alwaies in feare, though they ſee no water, but when they ſee it, their feare is much more increaſed at the beholding thereof; calling ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to minde their byting, with an imagination that they ſee a dogge therein: and they become apt or ready to vomit, becauſe the mouth of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke is affected with poyſon, whereby is ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp therein a certaine heauie and grieuous ſenſe that is imparted to the inward ſenſe, and is a cauſe that from the braine is imparted that loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and hurtfull deſiring power: whereby,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18279:22"/>like as if the animall ſpirit be rightly offred from the braine to the mouth of the ſtomacke, the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite is good, and thereto agreeth the attractiue power of the ſtomacke: euen ſo while there is offred from the brayne, a vitious or corrupt appetiting fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, there followeth loathing and aptneſſe to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, whereto aſſenteth the expulſiue faculty: which is the cauſe that they vomit vp ſuch water as they drinke.</p>
               <p>Heerewithall may reaſon be inferred for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling of two famous Phyſitians that ſeeme to haue vttered contrarie opinions or doctrines: that is <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Auicen:</hi> This man ſaith, that mad men die vpon the drinking of water, and <hi>Galen,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe ſaith, that the drinking of it is good for them. To which it is anſwered, that if the madneſſe be in the beginning, the drinking of water is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: but if it be farre gone, and the feare continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then doe they die by drinking thereof, becauſe the vitall ſpirit is almoſt wholely diſſipate, ſo that vpon ſmall occaſion and very ſpeedily it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulian Palmarius</hi> thinketh, that (whatſoeuer the right cauſe of their fearing of water may be) there is ſome extreame antipathy or contrariety betwixt that madneſſe and water, becauſe (beſide this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding feare of water) it hath beene obſerued by experience, that if the new bitten wound bee but waſhed with water, the bitten body can afterward very hardly or neuer be cured &amp; freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> madnes: for that the water by this antipathie driueth &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth this kind of poiſon ſo deeply into the body, as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18279:22"/>it cannot be fetcht out againe, or very hardly. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoueth ſuch as be bitten, to take heed of waſhing the wounds with freſh water. This opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Palmarius</hi> ſeemeth very truth-like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> very litle differing in opinion from <hi>Palmarius</hi> ſaith, that the poiſon of doggiſh-madnes followeth no peculiar temperament, but is a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the whole ſubſtance: which being commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to man, very ſlily or ſecretly polluting the humors without any ſenſe or perſeuerance of hurt, and by little and little creeping from part to part, as ſoone as euer it toucheth any principall part, it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbeth and greatly vexeth it, cauſing great thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe. At which time, if the ſicke doe drinke or take any liquid thing, they are tormented very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely in their inward parts. This cannot be by reaſon of any temperature, becauſe they feele one kind of torture whether they drinke hot liquor or cold; but by the peculiar nature of that kinde of poyſon, which as it is a poyſon hurtfull to man for the whole ſubſtance thereof, ſo hath it an antipathie or contrary diſpoſition in it to all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid things, by which it becommeth ſo exaſperate and cruell, as the inward parts by the terrible pangs and grypings thereof, are more miſerably vexed then otherwiſe they ſhould be. This ſaith <hi>Salius,</hi> I haue noted to be the cauſe from whence they haue euen from the beginning abhorred liquid things, becauſe all with one conſent, haue affirmed that by the drinking of them, they haue been exceedingly afflicted. After the tryall whereof, they haue loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed and deteſted all ſorts of liquors ſo greatly, as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18279:23"/>the onely ſight of them, hath giuen occaſion to turne them into the like tortures, and ſometime worſer.</p>
               <p>This opinion ſeemeth ſo well to bee liked of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dronchus,</hi> that he nothing diſſenteth from it. But otherwiſe, ſo different haue been the opinions of other Writers, as the true cauſe of this <hi>Hydrophohie</hi> or water-feare, ſeemeth ſo ſecret and hidden, as the moſt learned and ingenuous haue been and are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combred by the ſearch thereof, and therefore for breuitie I leaue it, and paſſe to the cure of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and fearefull kind of madneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>WHEN one is bitten of a dogge, and reſteth doubtfull whether he were mad or not, it were good to make a tryall, by moyſtning a peece of bread in the bloudy wound, and offering it to a hungry dog, which if he refuſe to eat, it is very like that the byting dog was mad. For this tryall hath been found more aſſured than the giuing it to Pullen. For ſo exquiſite is the ſmelling ſenſe of dogs, as they are able to diſcerne therby that poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous infection which they are ſo apt to be hurt by. But hens and poultry haue been ſeene to eat ſuch kind of bread or nut kernels as haue been moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the wound, without any hurt thereby.</p>
               <p>It were good alſo to note or hearken, whether he did byte any other creature elſe, or whether he were noted to be afraid of water, or the ſight &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of looking glaſſes, or other bright things.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18279:23"/>
               <p>If the byting dog were knowen or found to bee mad, &amp; the wound that he hath made be great, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to bleed wel a good while together, that ſome part of the poiſon may come forth with the bloud. But withall let the bitten member bee preſently bound about, three or fower fingers bredth aboue the wound, with a garter or ſuch like thing reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hard, for the better reſtraint of the poyſons piercing. For this kind of practiſe by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Galen,</hi> and the experience of others, hath been found very profitable in prohibiting the ſpeedy piercing of poyſon by the bytings of ſerpents and venemous creatures. Yet if the part bound doe grow benummed &amp; ſenſeles by the hardnes of the binding, let it be ſlackned ſomewhat, leſt the bound member might thereby be mortified. But if the bitten wound be in ſuch a part as cannot be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly bound, then let ſome aſtringent medicine bee applyed ſome reaſonable diſtance aboue the wound, ſuch as this: Take oyle of <hi>roſes</hi> and <hi>myrtils,</hi> each an ounce, of <hi>bole armenake, ſanguis draconis, myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils</hi> and <hi>ſumach,</hi> each halfe a dram; Temper theſe together with the white of an egge well beaten, and a litle vineger, then ſpread it vpon a linnen cloth, and binde it aboue the wound, moyſtning it with vineger, or laying to freſh when it is dry. Or if the reſt cannot preſently be gotten, then in the meane time till they may be gotten, vſe the white of an egge beaten with a little vineger. Yet alwaies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, that theſe or ſuch like aſtringent medicines, be applyed quite beyond the place of the poyſons abiding: For if the poyſon haue gotten beyond
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18279:24"/>them, they may be a meanes to force it further into the bodie.</p>
               <p>But if the wound be ſmall and nothing percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued but the foame or ſlauer about it, then waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the foame with the vrine of a boy, or with lie, or ſuch like, and then dilate or enlarge it, by paring awaie the fleſh round about, that the hole may bee round which ſome call circination. For by this meanes the wound will the more eaſily be kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and not heale ſo ſoone as otherwiſe it would. Which maner of practize <hi>Galen</hi> doth approue. <hi>Lib. de theriaca ad Piſonem. Cap.</hi> 16. Some only ſcarrifie or ſcotch the skinne round about it, that it may bleed reaſonable well. After the vſe of circination or ſcarificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let ventozes or cupping-glaſſes be ſet on with a good flame, and then either cauterize it with a hot iron or rather with a cauterie of gold, except the place be ſinowe and very ſenſible. This cauterizing is commended by all writers as the moſt ſure remedy for the extinguiſhing of the viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent matter contained in the wound, which though it be terrible to the eye, yet the pain therof continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſo long as that which is cauſed by a poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall cauterie. This muſt not be ſlightly done, but ſtrongly ſet on and deepely preſſed in, as <hi>Guilielmus Fabritius</hi> a famous and ſingular Chirurgion vpon his often experience heerein, ſeriouſly aduiſeth, ſaying, I ſpeake by experience. For the more the wound is put in a heat and inflamed, the ſooner wil the poyſon be drawen forth.</p>
               <p>After it is ſeared, let the eſcharre or cruſt be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to fall as ſoone as is poſſible, by often annointing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18279:24"/>it with a mixture made of liquid varniſh, the white of an egge and freſh butter. Or with freſh butter of it ſelfe as hot as the partie can endure it. And if the cruſt by theſe meanes come not off within two daies ſpace, then may it be remoued by ſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and handy operation, leſt by the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof the venemous matter that remaineth vnconſumed, may get a new ſtrength, and the vlcer be ſooner cured then is conuenient for this maladie. For it ſhould be kept from healing the ſpace of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Or after the ventozes be remooued, there may be ſet on horſe-leeches for the more effectuall drawing forth of the venemous bloud, and then to cauterize as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But if the bitten place be of exquiſite ſenſe, or in tender bodies, theſe meanes ought rather to be vſed to the parts next adioining then to it, laying or apply-more milde things vpon the biting. As if the bitten body can get one that will ſucke out the venome with his mouth, that is the gentleſt way, moſt harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and yet very effectuall. But hee that ſucketh the wound muſt looke he haue no raw or skynles, or vlcered part in his mouth, leſt he catch hurt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf while he doth his good will to help another. And though his mouth be whole, yet it is good for him to rinſe or moiſten it with ſome ſweet oile, before he goe to ſucking. For ſo hee ſhall keepe the venome from taking hold on any part thereof. Next to this, is commended the application of the fundaments of liue cocks or hens, hauing the fethers pluckt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about them and held to a good while together, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18279:25"/>if one die thereby, then ſet to another preſently, holding their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cloſe that they breath not. For ſo they will draw the more forciblie, continuing this as long as any dieth by the ſtrength of the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Some rather like that theſe fowles or yoong pigeons, ſhould be ſplit through the middeſt aliue, and ſo layd to one after another or yoong whelpes in like ſort.</p>
               <p>Such as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide the ſearing with a hot iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an actual cautery, may haue ſome potential cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie applyed to the byting, after the waſhing, ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying, and cupping thereof as before hath beene declared, among which kinde of cauteries, <hi>argentum ſublimatum</hi> tempered with ſome cooling oyntment is much commended, as a moſt helpefull medicine, and the cruſt which it cauſeth, doth commonly fall off within two dayes, if it be often annoynted with butter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aetius</hi> commendeth the laying of ſtamped <hi>leeks,</hi> or bread tempered with ſalt or <hi>onions</hi> or <hi>garlicke</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bitten place, but eſpecially this compoſition. Take of <hi>ſal foſsile,</hi> an ounce, of <hi>aerugo ruſſa,</hi> as much, of the ſeeds of <hi>Horehound</hi> a dram. Let theſe be kept dry in a box of braſſe, vſe them firſt dry, til a cruſt be growne on the wound, then vſe them tempered with the oyle of roſes till the cruſt fall off.</p>
               <p>In very tender bodies, ſome lay to the wound a plaſter of pigeons dung and greene <hi>rue</hi> ſtamped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Or <hi>muſtard ſeed</hi> ſtamped with <hi>wall-nut ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, garlicke, ſalt</hi> and <hi>honie</hi> laid to plaſterwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſius Paraeus</hi> affirmeth that <hi>treacle</hi> diſſolued in <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> or generous wine excelleth all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18279:25"/>to rub the green wound withall hard till it bleed, &amp; after the wound is clean wipt &amp; dryed, to lay liniments to the place tempered therewith; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the remouing wherof it is good to lay on <hi>garlick</hi> or <hi>onions</hi> beaten with <hi>ſalt</hi> and <hi>turpentine.</hi> With this only remedie he cured one of the daughters of the noble Lady <hi>Gron,</hi> that was bitten in the calfe of the legge with a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>I haue read great commendations in an old writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten booke of this medicine followings as ſure reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to helpe the byting of a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>Take <hi>wormewood, rewe, hony,</hi> and <hi>ſalt</hi> ſtamped well together, and lay it plaſter-wiſe to the bitten place, and it will draw out the poyſon, ſeaſe the paine, and take away the ſwelling.</p>
               <p>The very like is noted alſo by <hi>Leuinus Lemnius Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de occult. naturae mirac. Cap.</hi> 13. And by <hi>Ioh. Huera. de capitis morbis. Cap.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> preſcribeth an emplaſter made of <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, onyons,</hi> and <hi>wheat-cornes</hi> chewed in ones mouth, which hath beene proued very effectuall for the poorer ſort of people and robuſt bodies. It draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth the piſon &amp; dilateth the vlcer, but many times it cauſeth very great paine, which wilbe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what amended by tempering it with oile of <hi>Hype<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricon,</hi> or oyle of wormes. If it bee laid to euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, it will ſuffice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen lib. de theriac. ad Piſon.</hi> affirmeth that hee hath applyed plaſter-wiſe, onely treacle mixt with oile of roſes, with very happy ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>It is much commended, to dreſſe the vlcer daily with <hi>precipitata</hi> as a thing that both keepeth it from
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18279:26"/>healing, and draweth out the poyſon.</p>
               <p>Or mix <hi>precipitata</hi> with any conuenient oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or emplaſter, and ſome vſe it alone, becauſe it is very forcible to draw the poyſon from the depth.</p>
               <p>All theſe remedies doe cauſe paine more or leſſe, but <hi>Guiliel. Fabritius</hi> ſaith, hee regardeth not the paine they cauſe, ſo that it be not exceſſiue, becauſe paine in this caſe is very profitable; for with the attraction of his humours, it draweth the venome outward to the mouth of the wound.</p>
               <p>His manner was after hee had cauterized the wound, to lay vpon it bombaſte moiſtened with <hi>aqua-vitae</hi> that <hi>treacle</hi> hath beene diſſolued in, and after that to lay on this plaſter following being ſpred vpon linnen.</p>
               <p>Take of <hi>onions</hi> ſomewhat roſted in the embers of leuen, and the powder of muſtard ſeed, each an ounce, of <hi>treacle</hi> halfe an ounce, of the leaues of <hi>rew</hi> and <hi>ſcordium</hi> each halfe a handfull, mixe them in a morter by adding a little <hi>hony.</hi> The next day after this maner of dreſſing, he ſeparated as much of the cruſt as he could with a penknife, and then againe applied the ſame medicines, til the cruſt were quite remoued, and then to prohibit the cloſing vp of the vlcer, he thruſt a peaſe into it twice a day, and by this meanes kept it from healing as long as hee thought good.</p>
               <p>Some to keepe the vlcer open, and draw foorth the venome, lay on a plaſter made of <hi>garlicke, onions,</hi> and the powder of <hi>mercurie</hi> beaten together.</p>
               <p>If the vlcer be about to drie vp, <hi>Rhaſis</hi> aduiſeth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18279:26"/>to lay on a peece of the ſalt fiſh called <hi>Tunnus,</hi> or ſalt beaten, or to ſprinkle it with vineger. But neuer let it bee waſht with freſh water, but rather with pure wine, as <hi>Paulus</hi> aduiſeth, or with hot foamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>camomile</hi> and <hi>lapathum,</hi> that is dockes, boyled in water, to procure it to bleed, ſucking it firſt, or rubbing it ſtrongly with the hand, or with ſcarification, or by ſetting to of horſeleches or ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tozes.</p>
               <p>It is ſayd that the aſhes of a fig-tree caſt vpon the bitten place, being cloſed vp, will open it againe. But for the more ſuretie, it were good withall to ſcarrifie it.</p>
               <p>This plaſter following is much commended to lay on the ſore. Take of the aſhes of <hi>crabfiſhes</hi> burnt, of <hi>garlicke, mynt, gentium, aristolochia rotunda,</hi> each two drams: <hi>bay-berries, bole armeniake,</hi> each a dram. Temper them with the ioyſe of mynts and make a plaſter, and waſh the place often with the vrine of a yoong boy.</p>
               <p>This powder following, is very excellent to bee caſt on the vlcer twice or thrice a weeke. Take of the powder of <hi>precipitata,</hi> of bezer-ſtone, and the powder of <hi>angelica</hi> rootes each a ſcruple. Mix them together. This doth wonderfully draw forth the malignity, and is of great force againſt poyſon.</p>
               <p>Inwardly alſo muſt be vſed <hi>Antidotes</hi> that haue vertue againſt ſuch kinde of poyſon, as that which is mentioned of <hi>Galen,</hi> by the preſcript of <hi>Aſinius,</hi> made in this maner. Take of freſh water crab fiſhes dried and beaten to powder, ten drams; of <hi>gentium</hi> ſeuen rams; of <hi>frankencenſe,</hi> one dram. Mix them,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18279:27"/>and giue the bitten body euery day three drams in water to drinke, for the ſpace of 40. daies together. <hi>Aetius</hi> putteth but fiue drams of <hi>gentium</hi> to the reſt.</p>
               <p>Another mixture very like this is ſet downe by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ofcorides</hi> in this ſort. Burne crabfiſhes with the twigs or proinings of <hi>vitis alba,</hi> that is <hi>white brionie,</hi> and reſerue the powder of <hi>gentium</hi> roots thus: Take of crabfiſh powder three drams; with which may bee mixt the powder of <hi>gentium</hi> one dram and halfe; of pure wine ſix ounces. Let ſo much be drunke fower daies together, which being ended, let the double or triple quantitie be drunke certaine other dayes.</p>
               <p>Some compound them thus: Take of <hi>gentian</hi> roots two drams, of crabfiſh powder three drams; of <hi>terra ſigillata</hi> halfe an ounce. Mix a dram of this powder with ſome fiue or ſix ounces of the decoctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes, and giue it euery day to drinke. This compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition I like very well, and ſo doe I this which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, deſcribed by <hi>Ioſeph Quercetano.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of <hi>gentian</hi> and <hi>valerian</hi> rootes, each an ounce and halfe; of <hi>Conſolida minor</hi> (which ſome take for the herbe called <hi>Selfe heale,</hi> but other for the <hi>dayſie</hi>) of dry <hi>rew</hi> and <hi>penny-royall</hi> (that ſome call <hi>organy</hi>) each a handfull; of <hi>mummia,</hi> and crabfiſhes calcined each an ounce. Boile theſe together in wine. Of this decoction giue the bitten body, about two or three ounces in the morning faſting, for the ſpace of eight daies together.</p>
               <p>Vntill things of greater efficacie can be prepared and made ready, it is thought profitable to giue the bitten body ſome of the mad dogges liuer burnt to aſhes, and enioyne them withall to a conuenient
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18279:27"/>diet, as meats of good iuice, &amp; rather moyſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dry, &amp; that the bodie be looſe, &amp; prepared with opening roots that haue vertue or power to procure vrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aetius</hi> commendeth the giuing of <hi>Treacle,</hi> about the quantitie of a filberd nut, the three firſt dayes, ſaying that he neuer knew any fall into <hi>hydrophobie,</hi> that is the feare of water (which is the extreame and laſt act of this tragicall infirmitie) that vſed to drinke treacle. And <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> alſo vpon his owne often experience, giueth it the price aboue all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward medicines that euer hee made triall off. The powder of <hi>harts horne</hi> burnt, and the <hi>bezour-ſtone</hi> are very good alſo to be vſed heerein.</p>
               <p>Some beſide treacle aduiſe alſo the vſe of <hi>mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date,</hi> or the confection called <hi>Diateſſaron,</hi> (which ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially is commended againſt the byting of a madde dogge) to be giuen alſo, after the poyſon is ſpred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vaines and arteries, becauſe they thinke that the inward parts are heereby fortified. Howbeit <hi>Capinaccius</hi> ſayth, that the great Antidotes (among which theſe are the cheefe) ſhould not be giuen at all, after one is attached with madneſſe, although before that time they ought to be vſed with al ſpeed tempered with ſorrell water, or the decoction of <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patium acutum,</hi> which ſome call <hi>herbe-patience,</hi> or ſome other apt or conuenient liquor.</p>
               <p>There is no remedie more vſuall or better hoped off among the vulgar ſort, then preſently after the byting, to waſh the bitten body two or three daies together in ſea water. Which hath beene found very effectuall in ſome bodies of good complexions, or in light hurts, but it is not <hi>catholicon,</hi> that is to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18279:28"/>ſay it ſeemeth not in all perſons. Nether will it doe any good at all, after the firſt three or fower dayes, from the byting.</p>
               <p>This practiſe was firſt deuiſed and vſed by ſuch as dwell neere the ſea, whereupon ſuch as haue dwelt farther from thence, in imitation of theſe, haue caſt their bitten bodies into brackiſh water, which is ſo far from doing good, as it is indeed exceeding hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, by reaſon of the antipathie betwixt his kinde of poyſon and freſh water, from which it is very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle different.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe <hi>Corn-lius Celſus</hi> aduiſeth that ſuch as be entring into <hi>hydrophobie,</hi> ſhould ſuddenly bee caſt vnawares into a poole or riuer of water, and if they be vnskilfull in ſwimming, to ſuffer then to ſinke into the water, as it may run well into their mouths, &amp; then to raiſe vp their heads again. But if they haue skil in ſwimming, then to ſowſe their heads ſomtime vnder the water, that they may drinke whether they wil or not. For ſo both their thirſt &amp; fear of water, wil be amended, as he ſaith. But in this practiſe he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one thing to be looked vnto, that is, leaſt their weake bodies be caught with a crampe or conuulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which if it happen, he wiſheth them to be put into a veſſell of hot oyle, after they haue been taken out of the poole. But how weake a remedy this is, hath been by example declared before, out of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draeas Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cius Elpidianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some put the bitten body into a bath, and make him ſweat therein, as long as he is able to endure it, the wound being kept open that the poiſon thereof might the more eaſily be ſoked out, then doe they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18279:28"/>make him drinke a good draught of pure &amp; vnmixt wine, which is eſteemed a thing contrarie to all poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. This being done three daies together, they thinke the bitten body ſafe from all danger. This practiſe is ſomewhat agreeable to that which the Philoſopher before ſpoken of, vſed on himſelfe, that <hi>Actius</hi> maketh mention of.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Oribaſius</hi> would not that any ſhould aduen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to bathe themſelues, before 20. daies after the biting, were expited, and ſome 40. daies: and <hi>Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> admitteth it only in the declination of the euill, that is, after all other medicinall practiſes, which indeed is moſt agreable to reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> ſaith that the vulgar ſort of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie people, put ſo great confidence in the vertue of holy bread and holy water, that whoſoeuer eateth and drinketh thereof from the hand of a Prieſt, ſhall neede none other remedie then onely this for his cure. But of what force this ſuperſtitious remedy is, he ſheweth by an example of one bitten by a madde dog, who very orderly and deuoutly had taken this ſanctified bread and water, and had the wound well healed vp, as he thought. Yet about two monthes after, catching a great blow or bruſing vpon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his belly, he was preſently vexed with a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and a doggiſh madnes, with all the ſymptomes and conſequencies, that vſually accompany this manner of madnes, and very ſhortly after, in great wretchednes and miſerie, tooke his leaue of this world.</p>
               <p>After the firſt three or foure daies from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the hurt, if the venome be perceiued to be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18279:29"/>of ſo quicke operation, as it is diſperſed through the body, let purging be vſed, or if it ſeeme to be of ſlowe proceeding, as in flegmatike and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like bodies, whoſe humours are groſſe, and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges narrow, let a longer time be paſt before pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, hauing yet a care to apply conuenient reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the bitten place. And when purging is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued to be needfull, then let it be performed as the occaſion ſhall ſeeme to require, although the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be neither concocted, nor doe boile or mooue in the body. The like conſideration ſome hould of phlebotomie, though <hi>Salius</hi> can in no fort like of this in any body tainted with any kind of poiſon. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ancient Greekes, as <hi>Dioſcorides, Galen, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>baſius, Paulus,</hi> and <hi>Actuarius,</hi> where they ſpeake of this infirmitie, doe ſhow by their ſilence or not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of phlebotomie, to diſlike thereof: and ſome excellent men of the late writers, as <hi>Fracaſtorius, Fernelius,</hi> and <hi>Capinaccius,</hi> do diſſwade the practiſe of it. But ſuch as do approne it, doe withall aduiſe, that it be not in any wiſe put in practiſe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, leaſt the poiſon that remaineth then about the bitten place, might thereby be drawne from thence into the inward parts of the body. Neuertheleſſe, when ſuch practiſe hath beene neglected, as ought to haue beene vſed at the firſt, and the venome is perceiued to be ſpred throughout the body, then is it aduiſed as very requiſite, to open a veine, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if the body be plethoricke or full of humours, whether it be in the biting of a dogge, or any other venemous beaſt.</p>
               <p>Or for a more generall doctrine this may paſſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18279:29"/>that in bodies cacochymicke, (that is) where the humours be corrupted, or badly tempered (purging ſhould rather be vſed, then letting of blood. But in plethoricke or full bodies, letting of blood rather then purging. And where is both corruption of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and plenitude, there ſhould both be vſed, the conditions ſtill being obſerued that haue been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aduiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baptiſta Codronchus</hi> ſeing the diuerſitie of opinions concerning this point, and the reaſons <hi>pro &amp; contra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droph. Cap.</hi> 6.</note> as a man not well knowing whether part to approue, concludeth with theſe words. <hi>Nos igitur in hoc anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti caſu &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay: We therefore in this doubtfull caſe, hauing a reſpect to both, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that there ſhould be euacuation by blood, though not by cutting a vaine, but rather by ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tozes, ſet to the lower parts, by which may be drawne out more or leſſe blood as we liſt, according to the ability of the body, and ſo may both the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude be abated, and the venome be diuerted and drawne from the vpper, downe to the lower ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame parts.</p>
               <p>But now returning to purging. The tenderer bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may be purged with purgations made of <hi>ſena epithymum, polypodium,</hi> blacke <hi>hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bor,</hi> and ſuch like. But the ſtronger, with pils made of <hi>hellebor, elateri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, veratrum album,</hi> and the moſt vchement medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as <hi>antimonium,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> (a man of great experience in theſe doggiſhmaladies) preferreth the vſe of <hi>Elleborus albus</hi> (prepared in ſuch ſort as he ſetteth downe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any purgers whatſoeuer, in theſe affects,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. de affect. par. ium. cap.</hi> 19.</note> except
<pb facs="tcp:18279:30"/>in weaklings, fearefull &amp; extenuate bodies, ſtreight breſted, or trobled with a cough, or other affects of the breſt. His manner of preparing and vſing it, he hath ſet downe at large, and therefore for breuities ſake I paſſe it ouer, referring the Reader to the place in the Margent cited. This and other ſtrong purges before named, beſide their forcible expelling of the poiſon, haue alſo a ſecret qualitie, like either to the offending humours, or the doggiſh poiſon, by which they deliuer the body thereof.</p>
               <p>This following, is a very good purge in this caſe: Roſt a great <hi>onion</hi> in the embers, (hauing firſt made a hole in the top of it, and filled it with good treacle) then ſtampe it, and ſtraine out the iuyce with water of <hi>pimpinella,</hi> or <hi>carduus bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ictus,</hi> and mixe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a ſufficient quantity of <hi>extractum elleb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri,</hi> and a little of the confection of <hi>Hamech,</hi> and ſo giue it for a purgation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elaterium</hi> may be giuen to the quantitie of their graines in both, or ſome proper decoction. Or the ſeeds of <hi>Cataputia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some to purge alſo by vrine, make a medicine of <hi>Cantharides,</hi> mixt with equall quantitie of hulled <hi>len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils,</hi> and giue thereof halfe a ſcruple at once, many dayes together. This is eſteemed profitable, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the poyſon hereby, is led to the bladder, and expelled with bloody vrine.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Rhaſis,</hi> and <hi>Ioh. Damaſcenus,</hi> two famous Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, prepare <hi>cantharides</hi> as followeth. Seperate from them, their wings, heads, and feet, and infuſe them a night and a day in ſower butter milke, then drie them, and mixe them with the flower of <hi>lentils</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18279:30"/>and wine, and ſo make them vp in <hi>trochiſes</hi> or little round cakes, of a ſcruple-weight apeece. Of theſe little cakes, they gaue euery day one, in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient liquor, many daies together. And if it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the vſe of theſe, that the ſicke did piſſe blood, they gaue him new milke to drink, which did amend the acrimonie or ſharpnes of the vrine, remedie the bleeding, and ſo did they preuent the feare of water. Yet ſome of good iudgement and practiſe, bee very iealous and doubtfull in giuing <hi>cantharides</hi> into the body, though neuer ſo skilfully prepared.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the diſeaſe, <hi>cantharides</hi> are very profitable to lay to the bitten part. But into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ought none of theſe vcheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t purges by ſtoole &amp; vrine, be giuen in the beginning, while the poyſonous matter reſteth in the bitten part only, or neere it. Nether is phebotomie then to be admitted, as hath beene noted before, leaſt the hurtfull pollution bee drawen thereby from the outward to the inward parts, and therefore better to be vſed with the lateſt, than with the ſooneſt.</p>
               <p>If in any dieaſe <hi>Extrema extremis,</hi> according to the rule of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ought to be put in practiſe, then ſurely in this, as moſt, both of the ancient and moderne Phyſitians haue counſelled. For after the poyſon heereof is once diſperſed through the body, then will it not (as they ſay) be vanquiſhed without the helpe of extreame and very violent remedies. All which ought to be vſed before <hi>hydrophobie.</hi> For that hauing once gotten the poſſeſſion, moſt men are of opinion, that all phyſicke commeth to late.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the gouernement and dyet of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18279:31"/>the bitten bodie, it is thought beſt to lodge him in a chamber that is hot and very lightſome, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euocation of the ſpirits and blood to the outward parts of the body, and neuer ſuffer him to be alone, but accompanied (if it may bee) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h ſuch as with pretty pleaſing tales, and merry ieſts, or inſtruments of muſicke, or both, are able to giue refreſhment to his dulled ſpirits. Let no means be vſed to put him in feare, nor to make him ſorrowfull. His diet muſt be in a mediocritie, neither very plentifull, nor ſlender. Emptineſſe or want of eating, encreaſeth the euill qualitie of humours, which is a very pernitious thing in any malignant vlcer. He may eat of veale, mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, hens, chickens, or capons fleſh, and ſuch other as breed good iuyce, being ſeaſoned with the iuice of orenges, limmons, citrons, which he may eat by themſelues alſo. And the powders of tormentill, <hi>pimpinella, mary-golds, borrage,</hi> and ſuch other like herbes, very good to ſtrawe or ſprinkle vpon his meat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rabbi Moyſes</hi> forbiddeth the eating of pigeons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſaith he, they be very exceeding hurtfull for ſuch as be thus affected, through a ſpeciall property of ſubſtance in them. But contrariwiſe he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the mutton or fleſh of rams, though it breed but bad iuyce, for that it hath a ſecret property to do good in this infirmitie.</p>
               <p>All writers with one conſent approue and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the vſe and eating of freſh water crabfiſhes, for the natiue &amp; inbred propertie they haue againſt the poyſon of this malady, as often experience hath proued.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18279:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Creuiſes</hi> alſo boiled in good wine, are approued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulus Aegineta,</hi> aduiſeth, that ſuch meat and drinke ſhould chiefly be vſed, as is of force to dull and extinguiſh the ſtrength and working of the poiſon, and keepe it from ſpreading it ſelfe through the bottome of the ſtomacke: both which proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hee ſaith, are performed by drinking of pure wine that is ſweet and old; or by drinking of milk, and eating of <hi>garlicke, onyons</hi> or <hi>leekes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aetius</hi> approueth the eating of <hi>garlicke,</hi> and ſuch other ſharpe and hot meats in the beginning, but not after, leaſt the poyſon thereby might become more forcible, but he forbiddeth the drinking of wine.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, moſt writers doe eſteeme it very medicinable to drinke ſtrong wine at the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, as wel as to eat hot and ſharpe meats. And ſome like of groſſe and ſlimie meats alſo, that by encreaſing of obſtructions, may the better hinder the piercing of the poyſon to the principall parts.</p>
               <p>But after fiue or fix daies be paſt from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then will it be beſt to reduce all to mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as was ſayd before, and forbeare very hot meats and drinkes. Then will it be good to vſe drinke of meane ſtrength, in which are ſteeped the leaues of <hi>pimpinella,</hi> that is burnt, and the flowers of <hi>mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds.</hi> A Iulep alſo made of firupe of <hi>cichorie,</hi> and the decoction of ſorrell and barly, is good to drinke.</p>
               <p>This Iulep following, is very goodalſo to vſe. Take of the iuyce of limmons and citrons, each halfe an ounce, of the iuice of ſower pomgranates, two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18279:32"/>ſorrell water and roſe water, each an ounce, ſpring water boyled, as much as will ſuffice. Make heereof a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to art, of which it is good to drinke often.</p>
               <p>Roſt meats are not ſo good to be vſed, as meats boiſed, eſpecially in ſome liquor that opening ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples apt to procure vrine, are ſod in.</p>
               <p>Their bread ſhould be made of the beſt wheat, and well leuened.</p>
               <p>Of fruits they may vſe, walnut;, ſigges, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and ſome ſay that cheſnuts haue a propertie to doe good.</p>
               <p>Let ſuch as accompanie the ſicke at their meat, take heed they can not of any meat they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. And ſome thinke it dangerous alſo to drinke in the cup or glaſſe that they drinke in, except it be firſt very well waſht,</p>
               <p>The vſe of vineger and ſower fruits or herbes, is thought good.</p>
               <p>Some admoniſh the bitten body, not to touch the cornell tree, nor reſt within the ſhadow of it, or the tree called <hi>Sanguinaria,</hi> which is the female cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell tree or ſhrubbe, nor to ſleepe vnder the ſernice tree, but to ſhunne them for the ſpace of a whole yeere, becauſe theſe trees are reported to haue ſuch a kind of propertie in them, as will quickly haſten forward their madnes.</p>
               <p>Sleepe, eſpecially if it be much, is hurtfull, till the ſtrength of the poiſon be well abated, or till the ſicke be much diſtempered for want of ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Venerious actions ſhould be forborne a yeere together.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:18279:32"/>
               <p>It were very requiſite that the ſicke body ſhould be kept indifferent looſe or ſoluble, all the time of his ſickenes or infirmitie, and to goe once or twiſe in a day to ſtoole, and piſſe freely, if he can.</p>
               <p>Now for the better dilucidation of the manner of curing this kind of maladie, I thought it good heere to inſert the method and meanes which <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Valleriola,</hi> a very learned Phyſitian vſed, in curing one far gone toward madnes, by the biting of a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>This man was bitten a little aboue one of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſer. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Obſer.</hi> 3.</note> and thereupon was carried by his freinds to a village called <hi>Les Sainctes Maries,</hi> which of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſort is accounted a place ſacred or hallowed for the curing of ſuch as are bitten by madde dogges, where he was waſhed &amp; bathed in the ſea the ſpace of nine daies together; after which he was brought home againe to <hi>Arles</hi> where he dwelt, the wound being growne very grieuous. He looked with a writhen or warped countenance, vſing little ſpeech, and ſeemed full of meditations like ſuch as be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with melancholie. The wound was of a pale or aſhie colour, and full of venemous matter, and therefore ſpeedily to be taken in hand. Finding his body very coſtiue, he cauſed this clyſter to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him.</p>
               <p>℞, <hi>Malnar. althaeae cum ſuis radicib. matrum violar. branc. vrſin. mercurialis, meliſſophylli, ana M,</hi> j. <hi>flor. chamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, melilot. roriſmarin. ana, P,</hi> j. <hi>epithym.</hi> ℥ſs. <hi>furfuris macri, P,</hi> j. <hi>Fiat omnium decoctio in iure capitis caſtrati &amp; omaſorum, ad lib.</hi> j. <hi>&amp; coletur. In colutura adde cathol.</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18279:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:18279:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:18279:34"/>℥j. <hi>Confect. hamech,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 
                  <hi>iij. ol. violar.</hi> ℥ <hi>iiij. ſacchari rub.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Fiat Clyſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This clyſter hauing performed his operation, he preſently made the wound to be cauterized with a hot iron, and for the more ſpeedie remouing of the cruſt or ſcabbe cauſed by the ſearing, he anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it with a mixture made of freſh butter, the yelke of an egge and ſwines greaſe, and ſometime he mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Vnguentum baſilicum</hi> with it. While theſe things were in hand, he gaue preſeruatiues inward, for the ſubducting of the poiſonous infection: and becauſe he was a plethorike young man, and of bad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors alſo, he did both let him blood &amp; purge him. For he feared not the recoyling or drawing inward of the venemous matter left, becauſe a great part of it had been conſumed by waſhing in the ſea, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the cauterie, and for the remaining poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he thought it very requiſite to doe that now, which in the beginning might not be permitted. His cure was, to drawe forth as much as he could, by the wound, keeping it open almoſt 60. daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and diligently clenſing it; to ſtrengthen the inward parts with appropriate Antidotes: and laſtly to heale it vp.</p>
               <p>For correcting and qualifying of his melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diſpoſition and reſtrayning of the poiſon, hee cauſed this Apozeme or ſyrupe following, to bee made.</p>
               <p>℞, <hi>Borag. bugloſſ. amborum cum radicib. ſuis, lapatij acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum toto, ana M.</hi> j. <hi>ſummata tum fumer. lupulor. &amp; fraxini, ana M.</hi> ſs. <hi>melliſſoph. M.</hi> j. <hi>beton. tantundem, ſem.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18279:34"/>citri, acetoſ. &amp; card. benedict. ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 
                  <hi>ij. polypodij queru. recentis non corroſi, &amp; purum contuſi,</hi> ℥j. <hi>puſſulur. exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinaturum, N,</hi> vj. <hi>Fiat omnium decoctio in aqua hordea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea recenter facta ad lib.</hi> ij. <hi>&amp; colatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colatura adde ſuccorum Inmar. lupulor. &amp; pomorum redolentium ana</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>aceti,</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Fiat ſyrupus cum ſaccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro clarificatus &amp; aromatizatus cum puluere theriaculi Guidonis,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j.</p>
               <p>This is to be giuen fower mornings together, and to bee iterated againe ſome other three or fower mornings.</p>
               <p>After the ſicke man had vſed this ſirupe, eight daies together, and now appeared ſome notes of concoction in his vrine, and the groſſe humors ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſufficiently attenuated, he purged him with this purgation following.</p>
               <p>℞, <hi>fol. ſen. Oriental. mundat.</hi> ℥iij. <hi>epithym.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> j. ſs. <hi>aniſ. &amp; cinnamomi electi, ana</hi> ℈ij. <hi>trium flor. commumum, folior. meliſſ. &amp; beton. ana P,</hi> j. <hi>Fiat decoctio ad</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>&amp; cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. In colatura diſſol. rhabarb. electi; in ſero lactis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prini per noctem infuſi cum tantillo cinnamoni, &amp; mane fortiter expreſsi,</hi> ℈iiij. <hi>confect. hamech prima deſcriptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij. ſs. <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riacae elect. puluer. theriaculis Guidonis, ana</hi> ℈ij. <hi>ſyrup. roſarum ex infuſione roſar. ſyrup. de pomis, ana</hi> ℥j. <hi>Fiat Potio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this purgation, he auoided many cholericke, burnt and melancholike excrements.</p>
               <p>The next day following, he gaue him treacle tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with the powder of betonie and ſugar. For the bitten wound, hee cauſed a cataplaſme to bee made thus: Take of white onions in number three, make holes in the tops of them, and fill them vp
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18279:35"/>with treacle, then couer the holes, and roſt the oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in hot embers till they be ſoft, after which, beat them in a morter, and force them through a haire ſiue. This done, ad of both ſorts of <hi>ariſtolochia</hi> beaten to powder, each <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> iij. of <hi>galbanum, bdellium,</hi> myrrh, each halfe an ounce; of the powder of crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes, ſiue drames. Mixe them in the forme of a cataplaſme, ſpread it and lay it on the wound.</p>
               <p>After the cruſt was ſeperated from the vlcer, he prepared a mundificatiue, made of roſine mixt with the powder of crabfiſhes, and the rootes of <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtolochia,</hi> and vpon the vlcer he laid this emplaſtar. Take of <hi>galbanum, ſagapenum,</hi> and <hi>opopanax,</hi> each halfe a drame, of <hi>cuphorbium, iridis Florentiae, ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loc. rotund.</hi> and gentian rootes, each a dram; powder of crabfiſhes, two drams; of waxe a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie; of turpentine, two ounces. Mixe them and make a plaſter.</p>
               <p>This did drawe a wonderfull deale of filthie matter out of the vlcer, and kept it from healing.</p>
               <p>Inwardly hee gaue him this powder following, for the ſpace of fortie dayes together, about two drams at once, to drinke in bugloſſe water.</p>
               <p>Take of the aſhes of riuer crabfiſhes, ten ounces, of <hi>gentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> rootes, fiue ounces, of <hi>olibanum,</hi> one ounce. Mixe them together, and make a very fine powder.</p>
               <p>When he had brought his cure to the point of healing, he gaue the ſicke, <hi>epithymum</hi> in whaie of goats milke, and ſometime he purged him with <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catholicon</hi> and the confection of <hi>hamech:</hi> and many times he waſhed the vlcer with the vrine of a yong boy. For this a <hi>Auicen</hi> ſayth, doth forciblie draw
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18279:35"/>forth the venome. And laſtly he healed it vp, and recouered him perfectly from the danger of this cruell and fearefull euill,</p>
               <p>But now to proceed as I began: It is very whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to drinke the decoction of <hi>oxylapathum</hi> and <hi>pimpinella,</hi> or <hi>mary-golds,</hi> tempered with a ſpooneful of <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> that <hi>gentium</hi> and <hi>treacle</hi> haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in.</p>
               <p>Some country people haue made great account of a medicine made of <hi>rew, wormewood, garlicke, dayſie leaues, mary-golds, balme,</hi> and a little blacke <hi>hellebor, ſalt,</hi> and <hi>vineger</hi> ſtamped and ſtrained together, and the iuice heere of giuen to drinke euery other mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſting forthrice, which is wont to purge them vpward and downeward in ſuch manner, that they thinke, the venome of the byting is thereby ſo throughly expelled out of the body, as they will neuer be touched with <hi>hydrophobie,</hi> or water feare, yet in the beginning, while the venome reſteth ſtill in or neere the bitten place, I thinke it not ſafe to vſe it.</p>
               <p>When the malignitie of the poyſon is diſperſed into the entrailes or inward parts, ſome account the giuing of <hi>antimonium,</hi> to bee a thing of ſpeciall vertue, becauſe it maketh expulſion euery way, as by vomit, ſiege, and ſweat. For in this caſe it is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den but loſt labour, to purge with other then ſuch as be violent in operation.</p>
               <p>In outward applications to the wound, a hot iron (as hath beene ſayd before) is much commended: yet if three or foure daies after the biting, be paſt without the vſe of any other good meanes, it is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18279:36"/>commonly to late to vſe it, but inſtead thereof may ſcarrifications be made, and ſome bliſtering medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins as horſe-leeches be applyed.</p>
               <p>Such as are afraid of a hot iron, may haue a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall cauterie inſtead thereof, made of <hi>Vnguentum roſatum</hi> and <hi>ſumblimatum</hi> tempered together.</p>
               <p>Such as are vexed with this infirmity, haue many times a continuall hot feuer withall, for whoſe eaſe <hi>Aetius</hi> commendeth the vſe of a medicine or anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote made of nuts, as followeth. <hi>R. ſagapeni</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>op.</hi> ij. <hi>Thebaici,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ij, <hi>Croci,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> ſs. <hi>Lycij Indici,</hi> ℈ixj <hi>&amp;</hi> ſs. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis nucum iuglandium non valde veterum,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> 40, <hi>Miſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The doſe of it is about a dram at once in raine water hot, toward night, and after the vigour of the feuer, ſo that in the morning before be giuen an antidote of crabfiſhes, and at night this of nuts. For it is of very great efficacie to procure ſleepe where is great want thereof.</p>
               <p>After the cure is finiſhed, he aduiſeth ſuch as be cured, to be purged once a yeere with <hi>Hiera,</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, about the approching of that time of the yeere they were bitten in; and vpon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant day of their byting to take <hi>treacle</hi> for three dayes together.</p>
               <p>For further cure of the ſicke if need be, <hi>Paulus</hi> ſayth that <hi>Dropaciſmi,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sinapiſmi,</hi> with great profit be made all the body ouer. But the moſt effectuall remedie of all other, he ſayth, is the right vſe of <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratrum</hi> often practized and taken. Which <hi>Salius</hi> ſeemeth to approue, where he ſayth that the caſe is very deſperate and hopeleſſe, where this doggiſh madneſſe is not holpen by gining of white <hi>ellebor</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:18279:36"/>well prepared. It is good for the ſicke to drinke whay, Smithes water, ſorrell or lettice water, which may eaſily be giuen them before they begin to feare water.</p>
               <p>But after they once beginne to feare it, let them be kept from the ſight both of it, and all other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid things. For nothing doth put them into ſuch horrour, and trembling, and vexation, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as the beholding of theſe, and ſome other bright things. It were good alſo that they might not ſee ſuch meat as is prouided for them. Yet if they refufe to eat or drinke, they muſt bee forced therto: although this be noted commonly in them that they ſwallow with great difficultie.</p>
               <p>As there may be deuices to keepe them from the ſight of their meat that is prepared for their eating, ſo may drinke be ſpowted into their mouthes, or downe their throats, with a ſyring, or giuen them in a ſuckling bottle, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Some not yet come to the feare of water, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the point thereof, haue ſuddenly vpon the ſight of water, fallen very grieuouſlie into the feare of it, by the ſudden motion and ſtirring of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent and poyſonnous matter contained in the body, which in nature is contrary to water.</p>
               <p>Some very ſuperſtitiouſly take vpon them to cure this diſeaſe, with words and charmes; which becauſe it is vngodly and deuiliſh, I paſſe ouer as a thing much more offenſiue to God, then healthfull to man.</p>
               <p>When the cure is brought either neere, or to an end, by the vſe of ſuch meanes as haue beene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18279:37"/>it would be very profitable and to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, after a cliſter giuen if the body bee coſtiue, to cauſe the bitten body to ſweat in reaſonable ſort, for the vtter expelling and vapouring out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes and remainder of the venemous matter, as well by inward as outward meanes. And before the ſore be quite healed vp, a tryall may be made whether any of the venemous matter remaine yet vnremoued, by the application of ſuch things as haue beene before aduiſed, for to know whether the byting dog were mad or not, as the kernels of <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts,</hi> or bread &amp; ſuch other layd to the ſore &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to hungry dogs, but firſt the ſore place ſhould be ſo ſweetned from the ſent &amp; ſmel of ſuch ſalues, and medicines as haue beene vſed thereto, as dogs by reaſon of them, might not take any diſlike of the bread that is offred them. And alſo triall may bee made by ſetting to the fundaments of cockes or hens, as hath beene ſayd.</p>
               <p>And though the cure be as well performed, as the skill of the Phiſitian or Chyrurgian can deuiſe, and no likelihood of any future harme ſeem to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: yet for the better aſſurance and preuention of relapſe, ſome aduiſe as a point of good prouidence, that the bitten body ſhould be purged once euery quarter of a yeere, and once in fifteene daies to eate a little of the beſt kind of treacle.</p>
               <p>I haue not read in any mans writings that hath intreated of this doggiſh euill, how dogges may be ordered to keepe them from madnes, ſauing only in <hi>Plinie,</hi> or the citers of <hi>Plinie,</hi> lib. 19. cap. 5. who ſheweth that the ould Phiſitians before his time, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18279:37"/>to cut a worme, as they call it, out of their tongues, which indeed is no worme, but a ſinowy matter, round in the faſhion of a worme. And ſome to that purpoſe cut of the end of whelpes tailes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be fortie daies ould. And the ſame, <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith alſo, lib. 8. cap. 40. that the elder and bigger dogges, ſhould euery yeere in the dogge daies, bee giuen hen-dunge mixt with the meat that they eat. For in thoſe daies they are moſt apt to be caught with madnes; but if they chaunce to bee mad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vſe of theſe meanes, then to purge them with <hi>elleborus.</hi> But yet in my conceit, vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of that which before I haue noted, and gathered out of the beſt &amp; moſt iudiciall &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed writers, before the purging of them, there ſhould be vſed outwardly (if they were bitten by any other dogge) ſome of thoſe good remedies that are ſet downe for men, and inwardly to giue them treacle and other good antidotes vſed againſt this infirmitie. But the ſureſt way is to hange them vp, or kill them outright, leaſt being kept a liue, they miſcheiue others. But for the preuenting and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dogs from madnes, whether they be ſound or bitten by a mad dog, no meanes can be vſed more excellent &amp; effectuall for the ſound then while the dog daies laſt, &amp; for the bitten at any time to mixe with their meat, or water that they drinke, ſome of this excellent powder following, that Doctor <hi>Iulian Palmarius,</hi> hath ſo much commended.</p>
               <p>All the aduiſe, counſell, and manner of curing this fearefull maladie, carefully ſet downe by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; moderne Phiſitians, hath no further ſcope,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18279:38"/>then to helpe ſuch as are not fallen into <hi>hydrophobie</hi> or feare of water, which is the extremitie of this diſeaſe, and ſo hard to be holpen, as none finding the ſicke in that caſe, would aduenture the curing of them, but leaue them as paſt all helpe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery.</p>
               <p>Yet now of late yeeres through the carefull and commendable induſtrie of ſome notable men, there is found out an Antidote of ſo excellent and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vertue, as being rightly vſed, hath by much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience been tried moſt ſure and infallible, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for preuenting of <hi>hydrophobie,</hi> but alſo for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſuch as haue been attached therwith, ſo that the wound be not in any part of the head aboue the mouth, nor waſht with freſh water. For where either of theſe is found, there remaineth either none, or very ſmall hope of helpe.</p>
               <p>This pretious Antidote, or all-curing medicine, <hi>Iulian Palmarius</hi> a worthy Phyſitian, hath made knowne for the benefite of all ſorts of people, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon his owne ſundry trials thereof, that it is ſo excellent in vertue, as it will cure and helpe the bitten bodies, at what time ſoeuer they be bitten, yea though they haue neuer been purged, or vſed any of the meanes before ſet downe, or though they be vexed with the hydrophobie, the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons only excepted that are before noted. By which meanes, the ſicke are freed from many tortures that in other manner of curings, they be forced to endure.</p>
               <p>This remedie of ſo rare vertue, is made as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18279:38"/>
               <p>Take of the leaues of rew, veruen, of the leſſer ſage, of plantaine, the leaues of polypodie, common wormewood, mint, mugwort, balme, betonie, the leſſer centaurie, of each equall waight. Theſe muſt euery one of them be gathered at ſuch time of the yeere as they be of moſt force, which commonly is in Iune, about the full of the Moone.</p>
               <p>Let them be put ſeuerally into paper bagges, and ſuffred to drie in ſuch a place, as neither Sunne, nor raine may come neere them, leaſt they ſhould grow too dry, or wax mouldly. Thus dried, let them be kept for future vſes, but ſo as they be renewed eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeere.</p>
               <p>When there is occaſion to vſe them, take of each ſort equall quantitie, and beat them to a very fine powder. Of this powder, giue to ſuch as be bitten, halfe a dram euery day faſting, either out of a ſpone, being mixt with the doble waight of ſugar, or with wine, or ſidar, or broth, or tempered with butter or hony in forme of an Opiate, three how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before meat. Although a dram and halfe or two drams at once, be ſufficient, either for man, or any kinde of beaſt, though cruelly bitten, yet it will not be a miſſe to proceed to three or fower drams, eſpecially if it be long ſince the partie was bitten, or that he be growne into hydrophobie. If he be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophobicke or mad, let him be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſlacke or doe hurt, and then temper this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with wine or other conuenient liquor, and powre it downe his throat, whether he will or not, putting ſomething into his mouth to hould it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. This may beſt be done in the intermiſſion of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18279:39"/>his madnes or fury. But to one that is newly bitten, there needs no more to be done, then firſt to wipe and drie the wound, either with a ſponge, or ſome drie linen cloth, and then to bath it with wine or hydromell, in which halfe a dram of this powder is diſſolued.</p>
               <p>This ſhould be done twiſe or thriſe euery day, then lay on ſome ointment or plaſter, ſuch as is wont to be laid on other wounds, and ſo ſuffer it to heale, without any feare of hydrophobie.</p>
               <p>While this practiſe is thus ordred, there wilbe no need, either to alter the ordinarie diet, or to keepe the houſe, or to take any purging medicine, except the bitten body be vexed with hydrophobie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be taken in hand. For that being remoued, the humors of the body that bee diſtempered, ſhould be amended, partly by purging, and partly by good and wholſome diet.</p>
               <p>This noble remedie, was firſt receiued from a man of great nobilitie, called <hi>Iacobus Syluanus,</hi> Lord of <hi>Pyrou,</hi> as a thing worthie to be dignified by the authoritie and patronage of true nobilitie, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulged by <hi>Iulianus Palmarius</hi> a noble minded Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian.</p>
               <p>Admirable muſt needs be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the operation of this medicine, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it being hot in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature is of force againſt hot malignant &amp; continuall feuers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with moſt fearefull ſymptomes, ſuch as commonly follow the the byting of mad dogges: and in allages &amp; ſexes, of what complexion ſoeuer, and alſo in the helping of bruit beaſts. <hi>Palmarius</hi> ſaith he neuer knew it faile in curing either the new
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18279:39"/>bitten, or ſuch as haue not had aboue two or three fits of <hi>hydrophobie.</hi> This therfore being of ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full efficacie againſt this maladie, all that I haue ſet downe before concerning the cure heereof, out of ancient and late writers, might ſeeme needleſſe, were it not that this is not like to be alwayes in a readineſſe in all places, or peraduenture not prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as it ought to be. Theſe things conſidered, I thought it good to ioyne both ſorts of cure toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that where the one is wanting, the other may be vſed.</p>
               <p>And after theſe ſo many much commended, and experienced medicines, ſet downe by learned writers for the cure of this diſeaſe I will communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate one more, much commended vnto me from a friend, who reporteth, that this medicine hath beene often experienced, with moſt happy ſucceſſe, in the curing of wounds cauſed by the byting of madde dogges. And is made as followeth.</p>
               <p>℞<hi>Capitum Allij</hi> ℥ <hi>ij. fol: Ruta M</hi> j. <hi>ſtanni puluerizati</hi> ℥ <hi>ij. Theriaca opt. Androm:</hi> ℥ <hi>iij.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Boile all theſe together in <hi>muſcudine,</hi> ſo much as will ſuffice in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> the veſſell wherein they are being cloſe ſtopped, or if you cannot get wine, take ſo much Ale as will ſuffice to boile them in, and when they are well boyled, ſtraine them and let the grieued patient drinke ℥vij thereof at a time, taking ſo much a time at three ſeueral times within 24 houres. The firſt draught to be taken ſo ſoone as poſſible you can make this medicine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die after the patient is bitten; then take the ſecond draught, eight houres after that; and the third
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18279:40"/>eight houres after that, and ſo to continue the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thereof euery eight houres, for the ſpace of 7. or 8. dayes together. Or you may vſe it longer if you ſee any cauſe to ſuſpect danger, and towards the end, you may change it from euery 8. houres to euery 12. houres.</p>
               <p>And you muſt alwaies applie vnto the wound bitten with the dogge, the feces, or dregges, that were left of the drinke, after the ſtrayning thereof, and it muſt be applied to the wound very warme.</p>
               <p>And you muſt alwaies heere obſerue, that you are not to apply either this medicine, or any other, vnto the wound, vntill you haue (by ſome of the meanes before named) clenſed the wound, from that venemous ſlauer, and filth, left there by the mad dogges byting by boxing-glaſſes with ſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, and by waſhing the wound as before hath beene taught.</p>
               <p>Now for concluſion, I ſuppoſe it wilbe expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that after this my demonſtration and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of other mens opinions, aduiſes, counſelles, practizes, and experiments for the helpe of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, I ſhould alſo bring to light, ſuch peculiar knowledge, obſeruation and experience, as my ſelfe haue had at any time, in dealing with this kinde of ſubiect. To whoſe expectation I anſwere, that although I haue beene a practiſer in Phyſicke, aboue thirtie yeeres, and haue dealt mith many ſorts of infirmities, yet in al this time I ingenuouſly and plainly proteſt and confeſſe, that neuer hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath any cures of this condition, come to my hand, neither haue I knowen that any Phyſitian of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18279:40"/>mine acquaintance hath beene called to counſell for it. The reaſon heereof (as I conceiue) is, becauſe the byting of a mad dogge, in all places where I haue beene, hath ſo little beene regarded and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as they think it not of ſuch moment that it may need the helpe of a Phyſitian: But when any ſuch thing hapneth, they either apply ſome triuiall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine that they haue a good opinion of, to the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten place, or poſt them with what ſpeed they can to the ſea, though it be three or fower dayes before they can get thither, and then they thinke them as ſoundly holpen, as any Phyſitian or Chirurgian can doe. And truly, till by the reading of many writers of great knowledge and experience, I found it to be a matter of more regard then ſo ſlightly to be paſſed ouer, I eſteemed in a manner as lightly of it as they.</p>
               <p>But now hauing offred a perſpectiue glaſſe, to all ſuch as be willing to accept of it, for the better loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into the conſequences, and dependances of theſe kinds of bytings, I doubt not but the wiſer ſort of ſuch as ſhall haue the peruſall of this ſmall pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, will as occaſion may be miniſtred, more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thinke of it, then peraduenture they haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto done.</p>
               <p>But yet becauſe I am loth altogether to fruſtrate their expectation of ſomewhat from me, that may helpe to direct ſuch as be nouices in the practiſe of phyſicke, for ordring the cure heereof when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhal happen to be offred, I wil in few words ſhew them, how I would proceed in hope of their helpe, if any ſuch came vnder mine hand.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore if the byting be new and freſh, I
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18279:41"/>would binde the bitten member, about foure or fiue fingers diſtance aboue the bitten place, if it were in ſuch a part, as I might well doe it, or lay on ſome aſtrictiue plaſter, ſuch as before hath been ſet downe, for the better reſtraint of the poyſons paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, eſpecially in ſanguine or cholericke bodies, whoſe waies and paſſages are large, and the heat of their complexions ſome motine to the ſpeedier wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it, the quantitie and qualitie of the venome being conſidered withall.</p>
               <p>But in bodies of groſſe humours and cold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, the regard of ſuch aſtriction may bee the leſſe, for that in ſuch bodies the poyſon findeth not his paſſage or operation ſo eaſie. This done, I would note whether the wound were great or ſmall: if great, I would ſuffer it to bleed well: if ſmall I would enlarge it, and make it bleed ſufficiently (hauing firſt waſht away the foame or flauer of the dogges mouth, with the vrine of a boy, or ſome other good lotion) either by circination as hath beene ſhewed before, or ſcarification, or leeches, &amp; then ſet on a great cupping glaſſe, with a good flame, if the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten part would receine it, or a cupping horne; after the remouing heereof, I would waſh and foment it againe, with ſome ſtrong brine or ſalt water tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the beſt ſort of treacle, or with the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that <hi>Ambroſius Paraus</hi> vſed to the Lady <hi>Grons</hi> daughter, and laſtof all I would foment it in ſuch maner, as <hi>Iulian Palmarius</hi> hath aduiſed, with a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his powder (if I had it in a readineſſe) and giue of the ſame powder inward according to his counſell forbearing to torture the bitten body with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18279:41"/>cauteries as much as I could, and reſt only vpon the operation of this ſo much commended Antidote, which I would continue for the ſpace of 40. daies at the leaſt, ſtill fomenting and bathing the hurt place euery day as I ſhould finde occaſion, and withall vſe meanes to keepe the fore from healing vp al that while, though <hi>Palmarius</hi> affirme it needleſſe ſo to doe. But if this powder were not in readineſſe, then after the binding, waſhing, and clenſing with ſuch lotions as before are named, and cupping with ſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, I would ſeare it either with an actuall or a potential cautery, according to the doctrine before deliuered by the learned, procuring the fall or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming away of the ſcabbe or cruſt, with what ſpeed I could, and keeping open the ſear a ſufficient time, vſing euacuations, by purging, bleeding, and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in their due times, and inward corroboratiues and diet, &amp;c. in ſuch ſort as hath beene ſpecified. But except I ſhould ſee the greater occaſion I wold in ſtead of opening a vaine in the arme, vſe a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that none of them haue ſpoken of that I haue read, namely the opening of the hemorrhoidall vaines in the fundament. For ſo by all probabilitie the venemous pollution would be drawen downe thither from the princip all parts, without detriment to any other.</p>
               <p>If many daies were paſt, before the bitten bodie came to my curing, I would deale with him as Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Palmarius</hi> counſelleth, if I had his Antidote in a readines, or els as <hi>Franciſcus Valleriola</hi> dealt with his patient, or like differing from his practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18279:42"/>
               <head>Prognoſticke notes</head>
               <p>ALl that be bitten o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a mad dogge, if they bee neglected or badly cured, wil fall into the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of fearing water called hydrophobie, at one time or other; and much the rather if they be repleat with euill humors. But all this may eaſily be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if at the firſt there bee good order taken. For fewe haue miſcaried thereby, that preſently haue vſed good meanes to withſtand it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Salius</hi> ſaith that in his countrie, it hath been long time obſerued for truth, that if ſuch as be bitten by a mad creature, chance to touch the plant or tree called <hi>Cornus,</hi> or <hi>Sanguinaria,</hi> that is the Cornell or dogbery tree, within the ſpace of one yeere after his biting, he will certainely fall mad. And ſome alſo affirme that if the bitten doe ſleepe vnder the tree called <hi>Sorbus,</hi> which we call a Seruice tree, he will doe the like.</p>
               <p>Though the biting be but ſmall, and in the vpper part of the skinne, yet all ſpeed ought to be vſed for cure thereof. For otherwiſe it wilbe a very hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to preuent the miſchiefe depending thereon.</p>
               <p>The poiſon conteined in the ſlauer or ſpittle of a mad dogge, is hot and drie, malignant and conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, cauſing a diſtemper like it ſelfe in all ſuch as bee hurt thereby: which if it be ſuffred to lie on the skinne of any part of the body, and not quickly waſht away with ſalt water, vrine or ſuch like, it will infect the whole body, though it be not bitten.</p>
               <p>The fome or ſlauer of a mad dogs mouth, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ones lippes or tongue, will ſo quickly and eaſilie
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18279:42"/>peirce though thoſe parts, that it wil very ſpeedily induce madnes, if it be not quickly preuented, which is verified by a hiſtorie out of <hi>Caelius Orlerianus,</hi> which makes report of a certaine Semſter or Sew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that while ſhe was making a ſhirt, a dogge that ſhe no whit ſuſpected to be madde, ſnatcht at the ſhirt, and rent it with his teeth, which rent place ſhe afterward held betwixt her teeth to plucke it out ſtreight, that ſhe might the better ſowe it euen, but by this houlding betwixt her teeth, ſhe ſo lickt the bitten rent of the cloth, that the third day after, ſhe became ſtarke mad, and ſo died.</p>
               <p>That this is like to be true, heare what <hi>Guiliel.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>b. Obſer. &amp; Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>at C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>rur. Obſer.</hi> 86.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britius,</hi> a very excellent and expert Chirurgian of our time reporteth of the like, in his chirurgicall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcruations and cures.</p>
               <p>A certaine Matron or ancient woman, hapt to be met in the way by a madde dogge, who catching hould of one of her coates, tare it in two or three places, and ſo went his way without hurting any part of her body at all. This woman not knowing or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the dogge to be mad, at her comming home ſowed vp the rents of her coat, and when ſhe had done, bit of the thred with her teeth, without percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any hurt at all thereby, till three monthes were paſt. After which, ſhe began by little and little to grow melancholike and troubled with imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, horrible viſions and feares, and laſtly ſhe fell into a great loathing of water, wine, and liquid things, and moreouer to barke like a dog, looſing the knowledge of ſuch as were vſually in the houſe with her, and offring to bite them, continuing in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18279:43"/>this ſtate till ſhe died.</p>
               <p>The ſcratching alſo with the nailes, as well as the ſlauer may induce madnes, as <hi>Caelius Orrelianus</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth which was found to be true, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 602. by an inſtance produced by the fore-named <hi>Fabriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the ſame obſeruation cited.</p>
               <p>The ſtory is this. A certaine young man about 20. yeeres of age, called <hi>Daniel Perrin,</hi> in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt time of the yeere aboue named, was ſcratcht on the thombe of the right hand, by a madde Cat, but yet ſo lightly as the very vpper rinde of the skinne, which the Greekes call <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dermis,</hi> was ſcarce hurt, which, becauſe the yonge man had noe ſuſpition of the Cats madnes, he made none account of, and the rather for that he felt no paine of it, but on the firſt day of March following, he began by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to be very ſolemne, fearefull, and mooued with ſtrange imaginations, ſo that the next day hee was afraid to goe abroad. The third day of the ſame Month, ſaith <hi>Fabritius,</hi> I was ſent for, &amp; found him hydrophobicke, ſo exceedingly abhorring water, wine, or any liquid or bright thing, that hee could not endure the ſight of them. His face, necke, and breſt were inflamed, with the mixture of a blewe colour, ſweating and fainting much, and ſometime caſting himſelfe ſo violently this way and that way on his bed, that three ſtrong men could ſcarce hould him, offring to bite ſuch as ſtood neere him, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and quaking at the ſight of meat and drinke, &amp; in this wretched eſtate ended his life that night: Thus farre <hi>Guil. Fabritius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Catte no doubt, had been bitten before by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18279:43"/>ſome mad dogge.</p>
               <p>Hereby furthermore is ſhewed a moſt admirable force of this kind of poyſon, that is able to pearce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very nailes, being of a ſolid, ſenſeles &amp; horny ſubſtance, in ſuch ſort as to be able to worke ſo ſtrang effects.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Eſaias Meiſchuerus</hi> in his obſeruations hath this ſtory following. A Stripling or youth belonging to a noble gentleman, by chaunce found a ſword caſt vnder a bedſtead, with which a mad dog had been thruſt through many yeeres before. Which ſword he begd of his maſter, who bad him take it. The youth hauing gotten it, fell to ſcowring off the ruſt thereof, but being earneſt in this his buſines, he, chanced to catch a very ſlight hurt therby vpon one of his hands, yet as ſmall as the hurt was in ſhowe the ſequell thereof proued it great, in that very ſhortly after he became mad thereby, and ſo died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laurentius Surius</hi> reporteth that a certaine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlder in the Duchie of Wertenberg,
<note place="margin">Comment. reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in orbegeſtar,</note> on a time entertained ſome of his Gueſts with ſwines fleſh that had been bitten by a mad dogge, whereby all the eaters thereof became preſently ſo mad, that they bit and tare one an other with their teeth.</p>
               <p>Many are of opinion, that if the principall parts, that is the braine, heart, or liuer, bee affected, but eſpecially if the ſicke doc once beginne to feare wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there is no hope, or verie little, of recouery.</p>
               <p>It is reported alſo a ſgne of ſmall hope, if the ſicke will lie downe and tomble on the ground, and doe ſpeake with a hoarſe voice.</p>
               <p>A biting or wound quickly cloſed vp, is much
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18279:44"/>worſe then a great and large wound.</p>
               <p>No man neglecting meanes of helpe, ought to account himfelfe ſafe from perill, that hath been bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of a mad dogge, though he finde no alteration in his body within the ſpace of a yeere. For <hi>Albertus</hi> ſaith, that ſome haue become mad not till 12. yeeres after. <hi>Galen</hi> alſo and <hi>Guinerius,</hi> and other more (as hath partly been noted before) haue ſpoken of a greater number of yeeres that haue paſſed betwixt the biting and the madnes. And <hi>Alharabius</hi> of ſome called <hi>Alzaranius</hi> an Arabian, affirmeth that hee knew it fortruth, that the poiſon of a mad dogges biting, hath lien lurking in the body of the bitten, the ſpace of forty yeeres, before it hath ſhewed it ſelfe. And ſuch is the propertie of it, that the long er it lieth lurking in the body vnperceiued, the ſooner it killeth when it breaketh out into action, as <hi>Petrus Foreſtus</hi> by examples hath notified.</p>
               <p>The ſpittle or ſlauer of any beaſt, is thought to haue ſomething in it that is contrary to mans nature, as alſo the ſcratchings with their nailes &amp;c. and therefore is not to be neglected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auicen</hi> is of opinion that none bitten of a mad dog are paſt helpe, that are able to know themſelues in a looking glaſſe.</p>
               <p>It is not ſo dangerous to be bitten of a body that is mad by the biting of a mad dogge, as to be bitten of a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>Concerning prognoſtickes, thus writeth <hi>Petrus Salius:</hi> There be only two things worth the noting for prognoſticke ſignes in this infirmitie: Namely whether they bee only fore-ſhowers of madnes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18279:44"/>or to come: or whether the madnes be alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die preſent. In the former caſe there is hope of health or recouery, if the diſeaſe be oppugned with valiant and ſtrong medicines, and not with ſuch as be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and light, becauſe as yet the poiſon hath not wholely inuaded or poſſeſſed the principall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: but if it haue once gotten the maſtry of them, I am of opinion with the more famous ſort of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, that it is paſt all helpe and remedie, and therefore but loſt labour to vſe any meanes for curing thereof. And if <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> hath teſtified that he cured <hi>Eudemus</hi> ſicke of this diſeaſe, and that the Phyſitian <hi>Themiſon</hi> was alſo deliuered from it: though this be true, yet is it to be numbred among admirable things, and ſuch as exceed the power of man. Againe, if they were deliuered from this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, I am of minde ſaith he, that they were delt withall in the beginning, and not in the ſtate or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe thereof.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Paulus</hi> ſaith, that theſe were not bitten of a mad dogge, but that this affection was transferred to them, by ſome man that had beene bitten of a dogge, and that therefore <hi>Themiſon</hi> might be ſaued, becauſe he had it by a light contagion from a friend of his that had beene dogge-bitten.</p>
               <p>The difficultie therefore of this matter, being thus exemplified, may put the wiſely carefull in minde, the better to regard it, and looke to it in time.</p>
               <p>For it hath gone current from time to time that if once they be growen mad, they are paſt recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore the Poet <hi>Ouid</hi> who liued not long
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18279:45"/>after <hi>Aſclepiades,</hi> a Phyſitian of greatnote in his time could ſay:
<q>
                     <l>Soluere nodoſam neſcit medicina podagram:</l>
                     <l>Nec formidatis vlla medetur aquis.</l>
                  </q> Which I haue made ſpeake engliſh in this manner:
<q>
                     <l>The knottie gowte to cure, no medcins counted ſure:</l>
                     <l>Nor doggiſh waterfeare, that euer I could heare,</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The biting of a dogge that is not mad.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COrnelius Celſus</hi> ſaith, that euery biting of a beaſt, hath ſome kinde of venomnes in it: therefore the biting of a dogge that is not mad, ſhould not be neglected. For the paine that enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thereupon, ſome thinke to bee an argument of malignitie from the biter, becauſe the biting of any creature is more painefull and hard to cure, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſimple wound. Yet the paine of biting, more then by a ſimple wound, may be by reaſon of the tearing of the skinne and fleſh through the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the teeth, which rather doth bruiſe, then pearce the fleſh, except they bee preſſed very hard. And ſuch wounds as make round holes, or ſuch as be cauſed by ſtones, ſtaues, ſtripes and ſuch like, are alſo more painfull and hard to cure, then thoſe that be made with ſwords, daggers, kniues, and ſuch like. Wherefore whether a man, woman, child, horſe, cowe, ſwine or other creature, be bitten with a dogge that is not mad, or by a man, or ape, or ſuch like, let the biting bee preſently fomented or bathed with vineger and <hi>nitrum,</hi> called ſaltpeter mixt together. Or as <hi>Oribaſius</hi> aduiſeth, lay on a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18279:45"/>ſponge ſoked in vineger: or bruſe a fenell root and lay it on with hony.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulus Aegineta</hi> counſelleth that the bitten wound ſhould firſt be ſprinkled with vineger, &amp; then bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the open or flat hand, after which, to powre vineger vpon it from a loft, the vineger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt tempered with <hi>nitrum,</hi> and then to lay on a newe ſponge ſoked either in vineger alone, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with <hi>nitrum,</hi> and ſo let it lie the ſpace of three daies on the wound, moiſtening the ſponge with vineger when it drieth, for it healeth perfectly, as he ſaith. Or lay on <hi>lana ſuccida</hi> wet in vineger, or an onion bruſed with hony, or the toppes of <hi>origanum</hi> tempered with ſalt and onions in equall portions. But for bitings that are come to ſuppuration or matter, temper the meale of <hi>eruum</hi> with hony and lay it on: For it is ſpeciall good for ſuch bitings. If they be enflamed, anoint them with <hi>ſpuma argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi> or litharge beaten with water.</p>
               <p>After the place hath been formented, as before is ſaid, and the ſponge remoued, ſome account it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good to lay vpon the wound a cateplaſme made of walnut kirnels, onions, hony and ſalt boiled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and made vp with wheat meale, or <hi>farinaer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui,</hi> beaten together. It is good to keep the wound open ſome reaſonable time before it be healed vp.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amatus Luſitanus</hi> being called to the cure of one bitten by an Engliſh Maſtiue dogge that was not madde, kept the wound from healing,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Curat med. Centur.</hi> 2. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> 78.</note> a month to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to preuent all danger that might haue hapned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:18279:46"/>
               <head>Simples of great vertue againſt the byting of a mad dogge.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AGrimonià, Eupatorium,</hi> Agrimonie is of force to purge by vrine, and giuen either in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or the iuyce of the greene herbe drunke of one bitten with a mad dogge, after three or fower daies from the beginning, is of great effect, eſpecially if the body haue beene dealt withall before with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conuenient meanes. It is very excellent alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the biting or ſtinging of ſerpents, and other poiſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Allium,</hi> Garlicke, is of very great operation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all cold poiſons, and the biting of a madde dogge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alyſſon,</hi> Madwort, or Galens Moonewort. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len affirmeth it to be a maruelous herbe in curing ſuch as are bitten of a mad dogge, yea though they were entred into madnes. It is brought out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> but nowe ſome of our Herbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtes haue it growing in their gardens.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amygdala,</hi> Almons beaten with hony, are very good to lay to the biting of a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Angelica,</hi> is very excellent againſt the biting of a mad dogge or any other venemous beaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aphronitrum, Spumamaris,</hi> tempered with ſwines greaſe, auaileth much againſt ſuch bitings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnogloſſa, Plantago,</hi> Lambes tongue or plantain, is alſo very good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beta,</hi> Beet is commended for a good herbe in this caſe.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18279:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Betonica,</hi> Betonie is alſo greatly commended for ſuch bitings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Braſsica,</hi> Colewort, This herbe ſaith <hi>Rabbi Moiſes,</hi> hath a peculiar propertie againſt the biting of a mad dogge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bulbi omnes impoſiti iuuant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer fluuiatilis,</hi> Riuer crabfiſh, The aſhes of theſe fiſhes (as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith) are of wonderfull vertue, by the propertie of their ſubſtance, againſt the biting of a mad dogge, either alone, or much more by mixing them with gentian and frankencenſe or oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banum, in ſuch ſort as there may be offrankencenſe one part, of gentian fiue, and of the aſhes of crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes ten parts. This he learned of his Maſter <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrion</hi> the Empiricke, who alwaies had this powder in a readines, prepared as followeth. Into a pot of red braſſe hee put a number of crabfiſhes aliue, wherein he burnt them ſo long till they might bee beaten to very fine powder. This he did after the riſing of the dogſtarre, the ſunne being in the ſigne of <hi>Leo,</hi> and the Moone being 18. daies ould. This powder he gaue the dog-bitten body, euery day, fortie daies together, about a ſpoonefull at once, ſprinkled with water. But after three or fower daies from the begining, he gaue euery day two ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls ſprinkled as before.</p>
               <p>An other of his Maſters called <hi>Pelops,</hi> did no leſſe eſteeme the powder of theſe fiſhes, then the former.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oribaſius, Paulus</hi> and <hi>Aetius,</hi> prepare them much after the ſame manner. The vſe of them is very much regarded both of ould and late writers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caepe,</hi> Onion. The iuice of onions tempered with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18279:47"/>hony, rue and ſalt, is very profitable againſt the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of mad dogges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Centaurium minus.</hi> The leſſer centurie is an herbe of very great excellency for the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itis,</hi> Herbe-Iuie, or ground pine ſtamped greene with hony, is of vertue againſt poyſon, or the byting of any venemous beaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentiana,</hi> Gentian or Felwort, a dram of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the root of gentian or felwort, mixt with a little pepper and herbe grace, and giuen inward, is profitable for ſuch as are bitten or ſtung with any maner of beaſt, or for any that hath taken poyſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hyaenaepellis,</hi> the skinne or hide of the beaſt <hi>Hyaena,</hi> is of ſo admirable efficacie, ſaith <hi>Aetius,</hi> that if it be lapt about one that beginneth to be mad of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mad dogge, he will quickly be reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his wits. Or the powder of it burnt and giuen in drinke, will aſſwage the affection of <hi>hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phobie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imperatoria,</hi> maſterwort, the root with the leaues ſtamped and layd vpon the bytings of mad dogs, or rather venemous beaſts, will cure them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lapatium,</hi> Docke or herbe-patience is greatly commended by <hi>Aetius,</hi> to be laid plaſterwiſe on the wound or byting, and the decoction therof drunk, ſaying, he knew an ould man that vſed none other remedie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lichnis Plumaria,</hi> Fethertop or wild campion, the weight of two drams of the ſeed heereof beaten to powder and drunke, is good for ſuch as are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of any venemous beaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lycopſis Anglica, Echium, Alcibiadion,</hi> vipers bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18279:47"/>or wall bugloſſe: this herbe chewed and the iuyce ſwalowed downe, is a moſt ſingular remedie againſt poiſon and the byting of any venemous beaſt, or the root chewed and laid on the ſore, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meliſſa, Meliſſophyllon,</hi> Balme drunke in wine, or applyed outwardly, is of great vertue againſt the byting of mad dogges, or other venemous beaſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nepeta,</hi> Nep dry, is a very good herbe for this purpoſe: It draweth all the circumſtant moiſture from the deepeſt parts of the bodie, as <hi>Oribaſius</hi> writeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origanum</hi> wild marierome drunke in wine, is good againſt any kinde of poyſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oxalis Acetoſa,</hi> Sorrell bruſed and layd on, or the decoction thereof drunke, is of great force in this caſe as <hi>Aetius</hi> reporteth. Some vſe it as a ſecret, both in meats and medicins prepared therewith and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the wound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pimpinella,</hi> Burnet, This is a herbe of excellent vertue againſt the biting of a mad dogge. Of this herbe a hunts-man belonging to the french King <hi>Henry the ſecond,</hi> made report vnto Doctor <hi>Iohn Fernelius</hi> (while he had him in cure of a grieuous diſeaſe) that he knew by often experience, ſo great excellency in it for preuenting of <hi>hydrophobie</hi> or feare of water, that whoſoeuer being bitten of a mad dogge, did vſe to eat thereof certaine mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings faſting, either in a ſalade or otherwiſe ordred did neuer ſuſtaine any hurt by ſuch byting, which he firſt made proofe of in the Kings hounds, with notable good ſucceſſe.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18279:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Porrum,</hi> Leeke, the iuyce of Leekes drunke with hony, is good againſt the byting of venemous beaſts, and ſo are the leaues ſtamped and layd on the wound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Potumogeton,</hi> pond-weed tempered with ſalt and layd on the ſore, will not ſuffer any to fall into <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophobie,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aetius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praſium, Marrubium,</hi> Horehound is one of the three herbes of account that <hi>Galen</hi> mentioneth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ruta ſilueſtris,</hi> or <hi>agreſtis,</hi> the ſeeds of this herbe are very excellent to drinke againſt all bytings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scordeum,</hi> water-germander, or garlick-german<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is an herbe of very great account, not onely againſt all bytings of venemous beaſts, but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plague and other poiſons. This herbe and <hi>Centaurium minus,</hi> and <hi>Praſium,</hi> haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſayth <hi>Galen,</hi> as great ſecrets for theſe infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, among the ancient Phyſitians: but yet hee preferred <hi>Terra Lemnia</hi> before them all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorzonera,</hi> Viper graſſe is alſo reputed of great vertue againſt poiſonous bytings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Serpillum,</hi> wilde time is good againſt the bytings of any venemous beaſt either taken in drinke, or outwardly applied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Triticum,</hi> wheat chewed betwixt the teeth, and laid on the bitten wound, is very curatiue. So is the meale thereof tempered with vineger, or the branne of it.</p>
               <p>Balmes either naturall or artificiall, are very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent to dreſſe the bittenwound withall.</p>
               <p>Some remedies named in this treatis, I haue ſet downe in Latine, as I found them in the Authors
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18279:48"/>thereof, partly becauſe any Apothecatie vpon the ſight thereof, can prepare them in better ſort then other that are not vſed to ſuch practiſes: and partly for that many remedies heretofore (and too commonly indeed) diuulged and laid open to the vnskilfull managing of women and al-daring Empirickes, (though of themſelues very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, where they bee ordred <hi>per manum artificis,</hi> by the miniſtration and application of a skilfull artiſt that knoweth the true times and opportunities of their vſe) haue fallen out to doe great hurt to ſuch as they haue beene practiſed vpon, to the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credite and vndeſerued blemiſhing of the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſcience of Phyſicke, eſpecially in matters of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and phebotomie, and ſuch particulars as ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially belong to the ſecret myſteries of Phyſicke. For now are ſtart vp ſo many <hi>Theſſalian</hi> Phyſitians in euery corner, whom many not vnproperly doe tearme Dogle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ches, that this neuer too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended Science, containing in it the hidden ſecrets of all the whole Elementall world, is growne now ſo triuiall and baſely common, as euery ſmattering Surgion, euery Apothecarie, yea almoſt euery wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and euery botching Aſſe that hath read a little in Engliſh bookes of medicine, take vpon them to bee as good Phyſitians, as thoſe that in the vniuerſities haue ſpent many yeeres, and much mony in the ſuite and ſtudie thereof, and been dignified with the higheſt degrees of ſchoole, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that profeſſion, that the Vniuerſities can beſtowe vpon them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
